<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: graphdb | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.odino.org/blog/categories/graphdb/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-24T11:00:54+04:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GraphDB in PHP: time for the serious stuff]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.odino.org/graphdb-in-php-time-for-the-serious-stuff/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-25T12:09:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.odino.org/graphdb-in-php-time-for-the-serious-stuff</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This weekend I've been, for the first time in my life, in Poland, to speak at their national PHP conference.</p>

<p>We - as I was co-speaking with <a href="http://davidfunaro.com/">David</a> - introduced to the audience the fantastic ecosystem of graph databases, which are storage system using graphs as their primary data structures.</p>

<p>They rule for many reasons that I won't explain here, so I embed the presentation:</p>

<p><div class="slideshare" id="__ss_9831071"><iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/9831071 " width="100%" height="550" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div></p>

<p>We had a little demo at the end of the talk, and everything went fine except for the last feature we wanted to show; we eventually noticed that it didn't work because of a missing fixture in the DB, what a disappointment!</p>

<p>PHPCon Poland was really funny, although we weren't able to follow the 99% of the talks, as they were in Polish.</p>

<p>Saturday night was really intense because of the chats we had with the guys there about our talk and, later, the drinks.</p>

<h2>And now?</h2>

<p>On our way back to home we started working on the only huge miss of <a href="https://github.com/congow/Orient/">Orient</a> ( our ODM for OrientDB ): <strong>persisting PHP objects to the DB</strong> ( the opposite process is almost finished, it was subject of the <a href="https://github.com/congow/Orient/issues?sort=created&amp;direction=desc&amp;state=closed&amp;page=1&amp;milestone=3">beta-5</a> milestone that we have almost finished ).</p>

<p>Rock the graph out :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
