<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ZF2 | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.odino.org/blog/categories/zf2/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2012-09-21T02:23:50+04:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Contributing to the Zend Framework via GitHub]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.odino.org/contributing-to-the-zend-framework-via-github/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-18T13:05:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.odino.org/contributing-to-the-zend-framework-via-github</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So, I managed to integrate <a href="https://github.com/zendframework/zf2/commit/fe60cf8deb9888adfc7757dcec536dd24c021653">some crap I daily write into the Zend Framework 2</a> git repository, and here's how to do that.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Code</h2>

<p>The "real" repository of the ZF2 isn't on Github but, someway, they are managing to integrate <a href="https://github.com/zendframework/zf2">pull requests from the Github mirror</a> to the <a href="http://git.zendframework.com/?a=summary&amp;p=zf">real repo hosted by Zend Technologies</a>.</p>

<p>Thanks to this, you only need to fork it and work on what you'd like to change, improve or implement.</p>

<p>From my viewpoint, I needed to integrate into the <code>Zend\Service\Twitter</code> an API to retrieve the users who retweeted a certain tweet, identified by an ID.</p>

<p>So, first thing you should do is take a <a href="https://github.com/zendframework/zf2/blob/fe60cf8deb9888adfc7757dcec536dd24c021653/tests/Zend/Service/Twitter/TwitterTest.php">look at the tests of the class you are working on</a> to confidently understand how the hell your code can be tested: after doing so, you can <a href="https://github.com/zendframework/zf2/blob/fe60cf8deb9888adfc7757dcec536dd24c021653/tests/Zend/Service/Twitter/TwitterTest.php#L604">write a test</a> which should cover your functionality.</p>

<p>Then you can run your tests with PHPUnit:</p>

<p><code>bash Launching your test with PHPUnit
phpunit --bootstrap tests/Bootstrap.php tests/Zend/Service/Twitter/TwitterTest.php
</code></p>

<p>and see that something is failing :)</p>

<p>So, here's the actual work, you can implement your functionality using ZF2 coding standards without messing around things: in my case, it was all about <a href="https://github.com/zendframework/zf2/blob/fe60cf8deb9888adfc7757dcec536dd24c021653/library/Zend/Service/Twitter.php#L906">less than 5 LoCs</a>.</p>

<h2>Formalities</h2>

<p>Good: you have just done a work for the PHP community, and you are ready to ask an integration in the real ZF2 codebase: be aware, you need a couple formalities for completing the job.</p>

<p>First of all, download the <a href="http://framework.zend.com/cla">CLA</a> ( contributor license agreement ): print, fill, scan and send it to <code>cla@zend.com</code>.</p>

<p>If this seems weird to you, consider the fact that you are just signing a paper telling that you are not submitting copyrighted code and so on: so, Zend Framework, is just basically defending itself from jackasses :)</p>

<p>Try to understand it, please.</p>

<p>After that, you'll be contacted from a lady at Zend Technologies asking to create an account on ZF bug tracker: 2 minutes and you're done.</p>

<h2>Github</h2>

<p>Ready to go?</p>

<p>Go to your github forked repository and <a href="https://github.com/zendframework/zf2/pull/221">create a pull request</a>, better if you include a couple of informations with it.</p>

<p>That's all, folks!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
