<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: agile | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="http://odino.org/blog/categories/agile/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-01T05:32:00+04:00</updated>
  <id>http://odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Where is Agile?]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.org/what-is-agile/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-23T20:20:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.org/what-is-agile</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m a pragmatic programmer, not a pragmatic agilist.</p>

<p>If I had to be a pragmatic agilist during my career,
I&rsquo;d have been fired several times, and that&rsquo;s why.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The Agile rape</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/televangelist.jpg"></p>

<p>We hear the word <em>Agile</em> everywhere, thanks to the fact that
this is a concept 10 years old, brought to the public by some
of the <strong>greatest minds in computer engineering</strong>, who could also
describe <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Patterns-Enterprise-Application-Architecture-Martin/dp/0321127420">interesting things</a>
other than a cool way to have more fun and be more productive at work.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s face it: the word &ldquo;<em>Agile</em>&rdquo;&ldquo; has been raped over the past
5 years.
This is not because it became mainstream and everyone
wanted to adopt it, it&rsquo;s because once it was about to
become mainstream a lot of people heard of it and
wanted to integrate <strong>their own</strong> vision of agile
development into their IT infrastructures.</p>

<p>You read it: <strong>their</strong> own vision.</p>

<p>Take a look at the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lean_software_development">lean software development</a>: we have
the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mary-Poppendieck/e/B001IGNU3O/">Poppendieck saga</a>
and not much more; sure, there are a lot of books and a
lot of opinions about LSD across IT professionals,
nonetheless everyone takes inspiration from the infamous
<em>weds</em>, not from what they heard about what they wrote.</p>

<p>Fact, this is the reason why LSD is still a pure oasis
in IT<sup id='fnref:1'><a href='#fn:1' rel='footnote'>1</a></sup>.</p>

<h2>SCRUM</h2>

<p>Sure, one of the things I&rsquo;d point my finger against is SCRUM.</p>

<p>This lightweight agile methodolgy is probably on everyone&rsquo;s
mouth since 3 years, since lot of people adopted it and
it seem to work: nonetheless, SCRUM is failing and will continue failing
in preserving and communicating the legacy of the agile
principles, values and patterns.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/rugby-scrum.jpg"></p>

<p>The problem with SCRUM is not SCRUM itself, because I
think it <em>may</em> work in some contexts, but to the way
people interpret it and implement it in their own
processes:</p>

<ul>
<li>the focus is shifted from the IT team and the transparency
betweem the <strong>whole team</strong> to the <em>product owner</em>, which acts
as a benevolent dictator between the team and the customer</li>
<li>whenever you add a layer between programmers and the
customer, you introduce an overhead, which means a less efficient
communication</li>
<li>SCRUM masters often fail to facilitate, since they become
a bottleneck in the process: if a problem depends to the SM,
N people in the development team have to rely and wait for him,
while, if the team act as a standalone being, each part of it
can theoretically deal with problems applying a FIFO
principle (<em>first in, first out</em>, sorting problems by priority
and business value rather than age)</li>
<li>1 out of 2 <strong>certified SCRUM masters</strong> that I meet don&rsquo;t
even know how to finish <em>&ldquo;Individuals and interactions&hellip;&rdquo;</em>
which I find first offensive second really frustrating</li>
</ul>


<p>Yes, the last one is a merely pure personal observation:
still, there&rsquo;s no doubt about the certification itself,
which I find pretty overestimated.</p>

<p>[Formally] <strong>Certifying processes that don&rsquo;t have formal
approaches</strong> is purely counter-intuitive: sorry, agile
processes are not formal<sup id='fnref:2'><a href='#fn:2' rel='footnote'>2</a></sup>.</p>

<p>All in all the history of SCRUM and its adopters teaches
us that a few big corporations are willing to make a step
and try to embrace agile development, with the wrong approach:
if you will to adopt something that &ndash; oh, boy! &ndash; has a
manifesto you should, in first place, try not to betray
its values, <strong>transparency at first place</strong>.</p>

<h2>We are different</h2>

<p>The reality is that I never heard stories from the trenches of
an agile organization: ok, I read them, ok, I heard
something, but I never spoke with someone who illustrated
me a 100% adoption of one agile methodology,
no matter if SCRUM, crystal or XP<sup id='fnref:3'><a href='#fn:3' rel='footnote'>3</a></sup>.</p>

<p>I still think that embracing agile is the winning
option, (almost) no matter when and where:
share with me your stories, I&rsquo;d be glad to
give them some space here.</p>

<p>Still, agile&rsquo;s biggest problems are both
management and programmers: the management always
has a skeptical eye on new methodologies that
make their teams slower<sup id='fnref:4'><a href='#fn:4' rel='footnote'>4</a></sup> and
programmers often think that they should interpret
their own view of agile development.</p>

<p>Just a mention: I worked several months for a firm
who was selling itself as &ldquo;agile&rdquo; or &ndash; at least &ndash;
&ldquo;agile-prone&rdquo;, while no one ever did a retrospective
<strong>in months</strong>.</p>

<p>I spoke with PMs, I spoke with the CTO, I spoke with
the programmers: everyone had good intentions but no
one was <strong>eager to be the change</strong>, not to <strong>just talk</strong>.</p>

<p>Back then, it was really frustrating: so no surprise I
parted ways with that organization while account
managers are still there, working every day until 9pm
because &ldquo;<em>in this industry it works like this</em>&rdquo;.</p>

<p>&ldquo;<a href="http://www.agiledevelopment.it/2012/01/we-are-different/">We are different</a>&rdquo;,
they said.</p>

<h2>An agile and slower IT would just be a pain for our business</h2>

<p>IT is a bottleneck, <strong>get over it</strong>.</p>

<p>Still, most organizations think that the problem between their
ideas and their success is IT, since it tends to slow down and
raise doubts about estimates, delivery times and implementations.</p>

<p>Now, put things this way: you have a great idea, you
know it&rsquo;s gonna work.</p>

<p>Sadly, having an idea and implementing it are different things:
in a case, you think it and it becomes real, in the other
you need to work hard and in a very qualitative way not to
limit and ruin the motivation behind your work &ndash; guess
if IT fits in the first or the second case.</p>

<p>Still, <strong>IT is a bottleneck</strong>.</p>

<p>Be fine with it, that&rsquo;s why technicians tend to limit/screw
your ideas: they try to bring you back to reality and suggest
the most credibile solutions to your problems.
They have to be the bottleneck between a management&rsquo;s
childish dreams and reality.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/bottleneck.jpg"></p>

<p>Still, <strong>agile is a bottleneck</strong>.</p>

<p>Be fine with it, that&rsquo;s why agilists tend to enpower
collaboration: they try to find the best mid-term
solution for your problem, to help your business not
facing IT bottlenecks in <em>put-some-number-here</em> months.
They have to be the bottleneck between a management&rsquo;s
lack of knowledge and technology.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s why the management should listen to its IT
department and get some genuine advices about their
digital strategy and the upcoming issues that technology
could reserve them ( read &ldquo;it&rsquo;s stupid to spend 600k on
facebook ads for a mini-site if you dont have the right
servers to handle the groundbreaking traffic which
will come from ads themselves&rdquo; ).</p>

<p>I once worked in a company where the CEO thought we could
do whatever technologic project people would have
asked for: the CTO &ndash; pretty seasoned &ndash; was battling
everyday to get this guy understand that a salesman
cannot sell projects he doesn&rsquo;t know, at all &ndash; and yes,
that salesman was the CEO<sup id='fnref:5'><a href='#fn:5' rel='footnote'>5</a></sup>.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s funny how management tend to prove itself as the
dumbest department ever: you hire <em>some-area</em> professionals,
you pay them lot of money, you hear what they say,
you eventually ignore them<sup id='fnref:6'><a href='#fn:6' rel='footnote'>6</a></sup>.</p>

<p>Results?</p>

<ul>
<li>you could have saved a lot just hiring monkeys</li>
<li>you will make people working on stuff against their will</li>
</ul>


<p>Still, <strong>your problem with IT is you</strong>, not IT itself.</p>

<p>Now ask IT guys if they would like to work the agile way: 80%
of them will just tell you &ldquo;of course&rdquo; (at least in europe).
Now ask IT guys how many of them work in a company which
truly promotes agile development, following <strong>both
processes and values</strong>: 15% of them will get back to you
with a positive answer.</p>

<p>A failure, because it means that &ndash; still &ndash; IT
departments don&rsquo;t have the decisional power to
make their job better, easier and safer from
a business perspective<sup id='fnref:7'><a href='#fn:7' rel='footnote'>7</a></sup>.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/celtics.jpeg"></p>

<h2>Agile is not a reality</h2>

<p>Today I hear too many people talking about agile<sup id='fnref:8'><a href='#fn:8' rel='footnote'>8</a></sup>
while too few organizations succesfully implement it
in their own processes: simply, <strong>agile is mainstream but not a
reality</strong>.</p>

<p>You need the right people to truly integrate and implement
an agile methodology, this is a simple fact, and &ldquo;<em>the
right people</em>&rdquo; doesn&rsquo;t always mean experts, but people
who truly believe in agile values.</p>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phil_Jackson">Phil Jackson</a>
won 11 NBA titles while coaching Chicago (11)
and the Los Angeles Lakers (5), always using the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triangle_offense">triangle offense</a>.</p>

<p>Look at his teams:</p>

<ul>
<li>Scottie Pippen, Michael Jordan and Dennis Rodman in his runs with the Bulls</li>
<li>Kobe Bryant, Shaquille O'Neal and Derek Fisher with his first Lakers</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="right" src="/images/red-auerbach.jpg"></p>

<p>Simply, he was preaching the triangle offense and had the
right men at the right time.</p>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_Auerbach">Red Auerbach</a>,
the Boston Celtics legend, built several
( as a coach first as well as GM later ) teams
devoted to team-playing, respect and pride.
Counting up to 10 NBA titles.</p>

<p>He had Larry &ldquo;The Legend&rdquo; Bird, Kevin McHale, Robert
Parish, Glenn &ldquo;Doc&rdquo; Rivers, Bill Russel&hellip; I should stop:
he simply &ndash; again &ndash; had the right people.</p>

<p><strong>You</strong> say it&rsquo;s a coincidence: less words, more
people.</p>

<p><div class="footnotes">
<span>
Notes
</span>
	<ol>
		<li id='fn:1'>Don&rsquo;t be so enthusiast: in 2 years what happened to the agile software development will happen to LSD <a href='#fnref:1' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li><li id='fn:2'>Quoting Ron Jeffries: <a href="http://www.sviluppoagile.it/sfuggente-e-di-qualita">http://www.sviluppoagile.it/sfuggente-e-di-qualita</a> (italian article with english quotes) <a href='#fnref:2' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li><li id='fn:3'>Ok, maybe &ndash; in Italy &ndash; Ideato is the only example I can mention, but they are too small to count as a truly succesfull story <a href='#fnref:3' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li><li id='fn:4'>Following agile practices makes your team slower: that&rsquo;s a fact. For their first months programmers need to learn a new way to manage their job and handle collaboration among team members. Not to mention that when the team is experienced, kickstarting an agile project will always be slower, since in your first steps ( = iterations ) you tend to be more pragmatic and deliver with the highest quality, while cowboy coders start like the new John Wayne and end up screwing everything they can. <a href='#fnref:4' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li><li id='fn:5'>Now, that company is about to implode, guess why <a href='#fnref:5' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li><li id='fn:6'>It&rsquo;s funny how I was surprised &ndash; joining Rocket &ndash; when PMs and MDs were really about to follow your advices :) some of my previous experiences were really too far from this <a href='#fnref:6' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li><li id='fn:7'>Keep in mind that leveraging the technical quality of IT products ( like agile does ) means delivering software without a vendor&rsquo;s lock-in: as a result, agilists trust their job and try to deliver the best artifact they can, since they would be replaceable at any time of the process &mdash; see, everything for the customer&rsquo;s advantage <a href='#fnref:7' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li><li id='fn:8'>Myself included <a href='#fnref:8' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li>
	</ol>
</div>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Behaviour-driven development in PHP]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.org/behaviour-driven-development-in-php/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-27T23:32:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.org/behaviour-driven-development-in-php</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Behavior_Driven_Development">BDD</a> is an established practice which goes beyond test-driven development, assuming we are working on a agile-prone environment and our requirements are expressed as user stories or something similar: although this requirement is not mandatory, <strong>BDD&rsquo;s power is leveraged by using stories</strong>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It basically assumes that instead of focusing on tests, we should start our development process writing down <a href="http://docs.behat.org/quick_intro.html">a story that a parser can translate into a test</a> (a customer cares about features, not tests) a programmer can implement in order to verify that our software respects that story.</p>

<h2>Why BDD?</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s a pretty unconvenient question :)</p>

<p>Do you know why TDD is extremely powerful? If not, go check it on the web; if so, add to TDD the ability of <strong>writing tests in a ubiquitous language</strong>, letting the team share tests, user-stories and acceptance criteria without the pain of translating an actual story in a functional test that, for example, a customer could never understand.</p>

<h2>Getting started</h2>

<p>I was introduced to BDD by <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/pub/roberto-bettazzoni/2/12b/614">Roberto Bettazzoni</a> at the italian agile day 2010, during a dummy-proof session in which <a href="http://cukes.info/">cucumber</a> was used.</p>

<p>Although you can use Cucumber in your PHP projects (the implementation of the tests, however, should be written in Ruby), Behat is an excellent project which brings native BDD in PHP.</p>

<p>You can &ndash; and I recommend it &ndash;  <a href="http://pear.behat.org/">install it via PEAR</a>: just make sure you have all the required dependencies by running a simple</p>

<p><code>
behat
</code></p>

<p>after the installation: we had our daily WTF last week because <a href="http://mink.behat.org/">Mink</a>, a browser-emulator abstraction layer required by Behat, wasn&rsquo;t properly installed.</p>

<h2>The integration with symfony 1.4</h2>

<p>From <a href="http://www.dnsee.com/">our POV</a>, we use Behat in a pilot project written in symfony: you only need to install <a href="http://www.symfony-project.org/plugins/sfBehatPlugin">sfBehatPlugin</a> and configure the <code>behat.yml</code> file you find under <code>/config</code>:</p>

<p>``` yml
// behat.yml default config
default:
  paths:</p>

<pre><code>features: %%BEHAT_CONFIG_PATH%%/../test/features/frontend
</code></pre>

<p>  context:</p>

<pre><code>parameters:
  base_url: ~
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>and then you can run</p>

<p><code>
behat
</code></p>

<p>from the root of your symfony project: no tests, so let&rsquo;s write something!</p>

<p>In symfony, behat&rsquo;s tests are located under <code>/test/features</code>, and are a <code>.feature</code> file, looking like:</p>

<p>```
Feature: US-1
  As anonymous
  I want to open the homepage
  in order to know WTF this site is about</p>

<p>Scenario: anonymous user reaches the site&rsquo;s homepage, viewing it without errors
   Given I am on &ldquo;homepage&rdquo;</p>

<pre><code>Then I should see "This website is about crap" in the "body" element
 And The page loads correctly 
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>So, let&rsquo;s examine it:</p>

<ul>
<li>this &ldquo;code&rdquo; should be located in the <code>/test/features/homepageOk.feature</code> file</li>
<li>the <code>Feature</code> element defines the story you are working on (write it as it appears in your backlog)</li>
<li>every <code>Scenario</code> block identifies possible declinations for your story (user logs in with good credentials, user tries to log in with incorrect credentials and so on)</li>
<li>the sentences inside every scenario are the actual testers which are parsed by behat and <strong>translated in actual PHP code</strong></li>
</ul>


<h2>Translated in actual PHP code?</h2>

<p>Yes, because you have a <code>FeatureContext</code> class in which you define some methods that are your tests' implementations: BDD frameworks usually parse your scenarios' lines generating the code you need to implement.</p>

<p>Behat, for example, stores all its testers in the <code>FeatureContext</code> class, and when you write a new scenario, if Behat doesn&rsquo;t know its syntax, it outputs something like:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/behat.png"></p>

<p>so you only need to <em>copy&amp;paste</em> the method in your <code>FeatureContext</code> and implement the method with your logic.</p>

<p>Obviously, BDD frameworks have a set of predefined testers: you can see Behat&rsquo;s ones with</p>

<p><code>
behat --definitions
</code></p>

<p>you will see testers like <code>I should see [...]</code> which tests if the given text lies in the response.</p>

<h2>Producing ubiquitous documentation</h2>

<p>The cool thing is that, when you run your BDD test suite, you can export it in a fancy way, making it readable for every project&rsquo;s stakeholder:</p>

<p><code>
behat --out heyGuysReadThis.html --format html
</code></p>

<p>obtaining something like:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/behat-report.png"></p>

<h2>I won&rsquo;t be exhaustive, so what&rsquo;s next?</h2>

<p>No focus on how to use (<em>deeply</em> use) Behat here: it will be a matter of another post.</p>

<p>Then we will see how to use <a href="http://capifony.org/">capifony</a> to automatically deploy your symfony applications and produce acceptance criteria tests that will be used by your QA guys in order to test your brand new deployment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The art of agile development, my review]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.org/the-art-of-agile-development-my-review/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-11T13:43:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.org/the-art-of-agile-development-my-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve read this book 2 times, with a 2-years interlude: once when I was running my own company, a really small one, and the second time after <a href="http://www.dnsee.com/">DNSEE</a> started looking for talented developers on the market to join our team, in the middle of 2010.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="right" src="/images/art.agile.jpg"></p>

<p>In both cases there were interesting situations while reading the book: firstly I was trying to leverage my skill as a developer and PM, then I was helping a team mix together.</p>

<p>The second time has been really hard, because it really took several months to me to complete it, really dunno why.</p>

<p>Apart from personal thoughts, I would really like to share you some considerations about this book, a really cool one in my honest opinion.</p>

<h2>This book fits very well when&hellip;</h2>

<p>&hellip;you are a newcomer and want to know about agile development.</p>

<p>It explains very well every transition happening during an agile-based process.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t expect to read the latest from the agile universe, like Kanban or notions of LSD: this book is really focused on well-established patterns and processes and will deal with letting you master all the basics of any agile-based <em>doctrine</em>.</p>

<p>This is pretty useful when you can&rsquo;t afford being overwhelmed by notions, a typical situation while being a newbie.</p>

<h2>XP over agile</h2>

<p>The whole book explains <a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/">extreme programming</a>, not any other single agile methodology ( like SCRUM, Crystal or whatever ).</p>

<p>This is, IMHO, a pretty winning choice: XP has been widely recognized as the masterpiece &ndash; but also as the more difficult &ndash; of all the agile methodologies.</p>

<p>Just to be clear: when you know how to deal with the whole team, when your teammates know their responsibilities and are used to XP, each of them will suite perfectly as a SCRUM master ( although they will probably tell you SCRUM seems cheap to them :&ndash;) ).</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s why XP is a win-win trade while learning about the agile world.</p>

<h2>General considerations</h2>

<p>The book is really pragmatic and will help you in several situations: I really appreciated that, for every single change it would push you towards, it explains how you should face the change, how you should make other members of the team face it and in which manner, because of any problem, you can ( although you shoudn&rsquo;t ) ignore it.</p>

<h2>What I didn&rsquo;t like</h2>

<p>The only thing I disliked in the book was the chapter&rsquo;s organization: the usage of <em>etudes</em> and final considerations in each chapter sounded reduntant to me.</p>

<p>It may be a problem with me reading it for the second time: in fact, this kind of organization was really helpful to better understand what I was reading, how to adopt it and how to guide the transition <strong>from whatever to agile</strong> the first time I read it.</p>

<h2>Long-term retrospectives</h2>

<p>I read it 2 times for a single reason: to reflect on how I improved myself over 2 years.</p>

<p>How much of the book I introduce in my daily job and how I managed others to face my thoughs.</p>

<p>I really gotta say that reading it for the second time <strong>helped me so much realizing where, and why, I failed</strong>.</p>

<h2>So, is the book right for you?</h2>

<p>Don&rsquo;t you know how to conduct a retrospective? Need to learn what timeboxed iterations are? Can&rsquo;t figure out why refactoring and incremental design are <em>that</em> important? Don&rsquo;t know why you should take decision at the <strong>last responsible moment</strong>? Are you into a team and want to understand how far did you get?</p>

<p>If you can&rsquo;t tame these topics, sure, this book is right for you.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
