<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Category: CakeFest | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="http://odino.org/blog/categories/cakefest/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-28T21:04:06-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CakeFest 2013 Wrap-up]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.org/cakefest-2013-wrap-up/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-21T16:58:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.org/cakefest-2013-wrap-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am taking some time off to describe my last trip between
Burlingame and San Francisco for the CakeFest 2013.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>First-timer in the States</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/usa-flag.jpg"></p>

<p>It was actually &ndash; what a shame! &ndash; my first time in the States: given
that I find exotic cultures (SEA, Desi) a bit more attractive, I never took
the time to fly all the way west to visit the probably most discussed
country in the globe.</p>

<p>The flight, around 15 hours in total, was pretty stressful, at least for me, and
the visit VISA process at SFO took way longer than initially expected:
luckily, Italy is part of the VISA waiver program, and at least I didn&rsquo;t get
questioned too much by the federal agents at the airport.</p>

<p>In a couple of hours I am outside of the airport: without any accomodation, I head
towards the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tenderloin,_San_Francisco">tenderloin</a>,
probably not a wise choice :&ndash;)</p>

<p>I spent the first 2 days between Market and 7th, a pretty creepy location at night,
but very enjoyable during the day: from there it&rsquo;s very easy to take a cab or the tram
and get immersed in the tourist&rsquo;s life, visiting places like the Fisherman&rsquo;s Wharf,
Pier 39 or the Embarcadero.</p>

<p>Note to self: I should have checked about the America&rsquo;s cup before: since atteding
one of the races could have been pretty damn awesome!</p>

<h2>Location</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/cali-bike.jpg"></p>

<p>The conference was held right next to the airport, in
<a href="https://www.google.com/maps/preview#!q=burlingame+san+francisco&amp;data=!4m10!1m9!4m8!1m3!1d32160518!2d-95.677068!3d37.0625!3m2!1i1855!2i947!4f13.1">Burlingame</a>, inside
the Crowne Plaza hotel: the location was easily reachable by BART
and the airport shuttle, if you were staying in the city in those days.</p>

<p>After spending a couple days inside the city itself, I decided to
move to the CP for the rest of my vacation, as it was very comfortable
and convenient &ndash; by taking the BART you could get in SF in ~40
minutes.</p>

<p>All in all the Crowne Plaza was a pretty expensive place, but if you,
like me, are lazy and go for the easy choice, you will
find yourself pretty well there: every day (after the conference) I used to
take the shuttle to SFO and the BART there: with less than 20$
per day you would be able to move around San Francisco even though
you are actually sleeping 25km away from downtown.</p>

<h2>Welcome!</h2>

<p>The guys from the organization, especially <a href="https://github.com/jameswatts">James</a>,
did a nice job in welcoming people and making them feel at a reunion party
rather than at a formal conference: the atmosphere was very enjoyable and
having people coming from all over the world (Japan, Germany, Dubai, UK, &hellip;)
just gave it that international vibe that only these kind of events
can give you.</p>

<h2>The community</h2>

<p>I was actually surprised to see that CakePHP&rsquo;s &ldquo;official&rdquo; annual
event was a bit short in terms of numbers: I can&rsquo;t really compare it
to the <a href="http://www.zendcon.com/">ZendCon</a> or the
<a href="http://live.symfony.com/">Symfony Live</a> since I&rsquo;ve never been at the former
and my last visit to the latter was in 2011, but I am sure they get together
a few more nerds.</p>

<p>I think I could count up to 80 people in the main hall during the <strong>hot talks</strong>:
nothing bad, but I was expecting other numbers; for sure, having less people
let everyone talk to each other, as the atmosphere there was very collaborative
and group-oriented: personally, I would like to thank some of the guys for providing
much fun between talks &ndash; especially <a href="https://twitter.com/angelxmoreno">Angel</a> and
<a href="http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=104354&amp;authType=NAME_SEARCH&amp;authToken=9zAl&amp;locale=en_US&amp;srchid=277650061379771493631&amp;srchindex=1&amp;srchtotal=90&amp;trk=vsrp_people_res_name&amp;trkInfo=VSRPsearchId%3A277650061379771493631%2CVSRPtargetId%3A104354%2CVSRPcmpt%3Aprimary">Gary</a>.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/sea-lion.jpg"></p>

<h2>Conference</h2>

<p>Technically, the conference went way beyond my expectations: I didn&rsquo;t follow
all the talks (I know, I know) as I was also working during those 2 days, but what
I&rsquo;ve seen was very interesting.</p>

<p>There were talk about <a href="http://www.vagrantup.com/">Vagrant</a>, scaling/autoscaling and
Ember.JS: for me they were very valuable since
<a href="http://www.slideshare.net/odino/tips-and-tricks-for-your-service-oriented-architecture-cakefest-2013-in-san-francisco/3">I&rsquo;ve never used Cake</a>
and I was actually pretty scared of not finding talks that would inspire me
in my day-to-day job.</p>

<p>Kudos for making the CakeFest an event that a Symfonian can enjoy ;&ndash;)</p>

<h2>Aftermath</h2>

<p>Last but not least, thank you very much to the crazy guys working
at <a href="http://www.loadsys.com/">LoadSys</a>: it was so much fun to hang
with this crew from Illinois, even though they promised some pool
and we didn&rsquo;t manage to find a place with tables &ndash; what a pity!</p>

<p>Besides the fun and the jokes that evening/night was also very
interesting since <a href="https://twitter.com/joeytrapp">Joey</a>
caught me to discuss the latest developments in the JS
ecosystem, from EmberJS to AngularJS: I must admit that it
was a very inspiring exchange of ideas, and that we both share
the same doubts about long-term, <strong>maintainable NodeJS
architectures</strong>.</p>

<p> #sob</p>

<h2>See you next year?</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/sf.jpg"></p>

<p>The city was pretty good, the conference better than anything
I could expect and full of friendly nerds craving for new
concepts, ideas and patterns: all in all, I must admit that
the CakeFest is an event I would definitely like to join
again in the future.</p>

<p>Who knows where the <a href="http://bakery.cakephp.org/articles/predominant/2013/03/20/cakefest_2013_-_vote_for_the_location">crazy band is heading next year!</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HTTP/1.1, SPDY and HTTP/2.0, Again]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.org/http-slash-1-dot-1-spdy-and-http-slash-2-dot-0-again/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-01T17:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.org/http-slash-1-dot-1-spdy-and-http-slash-2-dot-0-again</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, tired like hell due to an almost sleepless night,
I gave my second (and last) talk at the <a href="http://cakefest.org">CakeFest</a>
in San Francisco.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It was a slightly remixed version of the same talk I gave at the
IPC in Germany last year, with a few addition and changes: I hope the
attendees have enjoyed the conference as well as my 2 <strong>small</strong>
contributions as much as I did.</p>

<p>As usual, the presentation is on <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/odino/http-colon-slash-slash-end-of-the-road-cakefest-2013-in-san-francisco">slideshare</a>:
here are the slides for the lazy ones :)</p>

<p><div class="slideshare" id="__ss_25801971"><iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/25801971 " width="850" height="730" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div></p>

<p>Cheers!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tips and Tricks for You Service-Oriented Architecture]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.org/tips-and-tricks-for-you-service-oriented-architecture/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-31T19:05:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.org/tips-and-tricks-for-you-service-oriented-architecture</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I gave the first of my 2 presentations scheduled for the
<a href="http://cakefest.org">CakeFest</a> here in San Francisco,
&ldquo;<a href="http://www.slideshare.net/odino/tips-and-tricks-for-your-service-oriented-architecture-cakefest-2013-in-san-francisco">Tips and Tricks for your SOA</a>&rdquo;.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It basically contains a few tips derived from our experience at
<a href="http://en-ae.namshi.com">Namshi</a> while building our own service-oriented
architecture, and I hope, since there&rsquo;s not <em>that</em> much material
about SOA out there, that this can serve as a good feedback from who
is actually embracing this architectural style.</p>

<p>As always, the slides are on <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/odino/tips-and-tricks-for-your-service-oriented-architecture-cakefest-2013-in-san-francisco">slideshare</a>,
and I&rsquo;m embedding the presentation
here for those who immediately want to have a look at it:</p>

<p><div class="slideshare" id="__ss_25786089"><iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/25786089 " width="850" height="730" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div></p>

<p>Tomorrow, as per the conference&rsquo;s schedule, I will be giving my other talk,
&ldquo;HTTP colon slash slash: end of the road?&rdquo;, a remake of what I
presented at the <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/odino/http-colon-slash-slash-the-end-of-the-road">IPC in Mainz last year</a>,
with some more contents and &ndash; hopefully &ndash; fancier slides :-P</p>

<p>Cheers!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>