<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Category: Fun | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="https://odino.org/categories/fun/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2021-07-18T10:30:01+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Message to All the Tech Teams Out There: Start Doing Tech Trivias]]></title>
    <link href="https://odino.org/a-message-to-all-the-tech-teams-out-there-start-doing-tech-trivias/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-01T00:01:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://odino.org/a-message-to-all-the-tech-teams-out-there-start-doing-tech-trivias</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/trivia2.png"></p>

<p>Every now and then you end up with a silly, stupid and simple idea
that turns out to be an epic win: I am firmly convinced that introducing
Tech Trivias was one of these ideas for <a href="http://tech.namshi.com">our team</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Motivation</h2>

<p>Too often we simply forget that work is not always as
fun as it should be: we would all like to be able
to <a href="https://github.com/namshi">write OS libraries</a> at our jobs, to work on cool
technologies like <a href="https://facebook.github.io/react-native/">React Native</a> or introducing new concepts,
like <a href="https://developers.google.com/web/progressive-web-apps/">Progressive Web Apps</a>, in our codebase<sup id='fnref:1'><a href='#fn:1' rel='footnote'>1</a></sup>, but
the reality is that bugfixes, meetings and testing often get in
the way of more exciting stuff.</p>

<p>To alleviate the &ldquo;pain&rdquo; of having a real-world job<sup id='fnref:2'><a href='#fn:2' rel='footnote'>2</a></sup>,
I decided to start playing, every few weeks, a game called <em>Tech Trivia</em>,
where the <a href="http://tech.namshi.com/team/">Namshi team</a> is divided
in two, heterogeneous teams battling to win the game.</p>

<p>The result?</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/trivia.png"></p>

<h2>What is a Tech Trivia?</h2>

<p>Without further ado, let me show you what we&rsquo;re talking about:</p>

<iframe src="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1QtC75iYmMWP33mdrXbQCbnQf3rTuP8Kqx8DETfrw9XY/embed?start=false&loop=false&delayms=60000" frameborder="0" width="600" height="420" allowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" webkitallowfullscreen="true"></iframe>


<p>As you might have guessed, Tech Trivia is just a sequence of
tech-related questions / games that the teams need play
to accumulate points and beat the other team &mdash; each Trivia consists
in 4/5 games that are played for around 5 / 10 minutes, adding up
to a total of one hour (or two, depending how hooligan-ish your team is :)).</p>

<p>Until now we held 2 Tech Trivia sessions and the games we&rsquo;ve played were
quite fun! Among the ones that we liked / played the most:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>random questions</strong>: ask a question, the first team that comes up with the right answer gets a point. If they give a wrong answer they get a -1 (this is so that individuals are discouraged to try without consulting with the rest of the team). An example would be <em>&ldquo;what is a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nibble">nibble</a>?&rdquo;</em></li>
<li><strong>let me lie for you</strong>: ask the teams a question, tell them to make up an answer and communicate it to you secretly (ie. via slack). Then read the question again and provide 4 answers: the right one, the 2 ones that the teams gave you and a wrong one you make up. Each team picks the answer they deem correct &mdash; if they pick correctly they get 1 point, if they pick the other team&rsquo;s answer the give them 1 point. This game was inspired by <a href="http://jackboxgames.com/project/fibbage/">fibbage</a></li>
<li><strong>coding challenge</strong>: this is self-explanatory. Time-boxing is a must: for example, in rounds of 10  minutes, you can reward the first team to come up with a working solution with 10 points. If no one has it, start a new time-boxed session, but the reward will only be 5 points now, and so on and so forth. Sorting problems are generally good for this game :)</li>
<li><strong>choose your destiny</strong>: create 3 buckets (easy / mid / hard) of questions and ask each team what kind of question they want. Points are relative to the difficulty (ie. 1 / 3 / 5 and -3 / -1 / 0 if they get it wrong). Go ahead until each team has answered 4/5 questions. Here teams can actually pick their own destiny as they would know how the score is and what kind of questions they should pick in order to rally from a deficit or distance the other team. Example questions could be: <em>&ldquo;name all prime numbers between 40 and 60&rdquo;</em> (<strong>easy</strong>) / <em>&ldquo;name 5 sorting algorithms&rdquo;</em> (<strong>mid</strong>) / <em>&ldquo;Open addressing is a tecnique used to handle collisions in hashtables. How does it work?&rdquo;</em> (<strong>hard</strong>)</li>
</ul>


<p>At the end of each game give the teams a recap of the score, let them regroup and
get ready for the next game. When the Trivia is over, get the trophies out and hand
them to the winners!</p>

<p>You shouldn&rsquo;t forget to also reward the losers though &mdash;
at the end of the day it&rsquo;s  just a game! Last time, for example, we gave everyone
~$50 to spend on <a href="https://www.udemy.com/">udemy</a> courses.</p>

<h2>FAQ</h2>

<p><strong>Who moderates the game?</strong></p>

<p>You can pick any of the guys, but I would advise you
to get someone who has a bit of authority and can pull
some stunts off (read below ;&ndash;)).</p>

<p><strong>What if one team is too good and the score is so unbalanced?</strong></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s where the moderator has to play an integral part
of the game: try to balance the game and make sure you make
it a little bit harder for the guys who are leading &mdash; you&rsquo;re
definitely not going to be very popular :)</p>

<p><strong>How do you form teams?</strong></p>

<p>We simply split teams and try to make sure that everyone
has a field / technology covered, ie. a team should always
have 1 linux guy, a frontend engineer and a backend one.</p>

<p>To be fair, that also depends on who plays the game:
if you are playing Tech Trivia amongst backend developers,
then try to keep away from a lot of UI questions.</p>

<p><strong>Where did all of this come from?</strong></p>

<p>My wife and I really enjoy <a href="http://jackboxgames.com/project/fibbage/">fibbage</a>,
a nice on-line game meant to be played among friends.
Seeing how much fun we have playing it, I thought we could
do something similar at work.</p>

<p><strong>Why just every few weeks?</strong></p>

<p>Preparing the games actually takes a while: you will need to
think of a bunch of questions and game formats, which isn&rsquo;t
always straightforward.</p>

<p>Coupling that with the fact that you might wanna get some
hardware (ie. throphies for the game, an hourglass to time
the coding challenges) you understand that&rsquo;s not something
that you can easily do every week.</p>

<p><strong>What about remote teams?</strong></p>

<p>No question, it would be harder to play with a
remote team &mdash; not impossible but definitely
harder.</p>

<p><a href="https://ae.linkedin.com/in/filippodesantis">One of our engineers</a>,
though, works remotely and took part to the games, so
it&rsquo;s definitely something that you can manage.</p>

<p><strong>How would a UI engineer know about linux internals?</strong></p>

<p>This is the point of the game: to challenge people on stuff
that they might not know but <strong>use</strong> everyday. A UI engineer
is surely used to <code>chmod</code> files and directories but probably
doesn&rsquo;t know why permissions go up to the number <code>7</code>.</p>

<p>He will probably have someone in his team that knows the answer,
so his team isn&rsquo;t penalized &mdash; and at the end of the day he
is probably going to learn something really useful about a technology
that he uses on a daily basis.</p>

<h2>In the end&hellip;</h2>

<p>A Tech Trivia is an opportunity to learn new things, explore some aspects of
technology / math / probability that we&rsquo;re usually never exposed to, do some
solid team-building and have fun together.</p>

<p>I am extremely happy to work in an organization that encourages
this kind of activities &mdash; the guys in our team seem to enjoy it a lot so I
foresee a lot of Trivia battles in the upcoming months.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d be pretty happy to hear your feedback and suggestions if you have
any &mdash; and I&rsquo;d be even happier to hear that you&rsquo;re doing Tech Trivias as well! :)</p>

<p><div class="footnotes">
<span>
Notes
</span>
	<ol>
		<li id='fn:1'>BTW, we&rsquo;re doing all 3 of them, so you should probably consider joining us! <a href="http://tech.namshi.com/join-us/">http://tech.namshi.com/join-us/</a> :) <a href='#fnref:1' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li><li id='fn:2'>Sarcasm intended <a href='#fnref:2' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li>
	</ol>
</div>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>