<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: job | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="http://odino.org/blog/categories/job/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-26T15:39:40-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[7 reasons why working for Namshi is great]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.org/7-reasons-why-working-at-namshi-is-great/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-17T17:44:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.org/7-reasons-why-working-at-namshi-is-great</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been working for <a href="http://namshi.com">Namshi</a> for almost 2
years now and I thought it would be interesting to share some
of the reasons why I consider this an ideal place, at the moment.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Some of these points can be extended to the company in general,
while some of them are related to the <a href="http://tech.namshi.com">tech department</a>.
All in all I&rsquo;d like to share my experience and what I feel when
I enter (sometimes late) in the office.</p>

<h2>Young and talented people</h2>

<p><img class="right <a" src="href="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7353/11924599125_b40b12de0d_n.jpg">http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7353/11924599125_b40b12de0d_n.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>Here I might repeat what you might have heard on the internet
about <a href="http://www.rocket-internet.de/ventures">Rocket Internet and its ventures</a>,
but working for one of them will make you cross paths with some
of the brightest youngsters across the industry.</p>

<p>If I were to mention everyone, the list would be too long to
fit in this post (and it would grow, like us, as they days go by)
but by walking around the office you can immediately feel
how <strong>many young people are pushing themselves to the max</strong> in
order to make the business as succesfull as possible.</p>

<p>I happen to live with my colleague
<a href="http://ae.linkedin.com/in/casuccioalex">Alessandro</a>,
a <a href="http://www.unibocconi.eu/wps/wcm/connect/Bocconi/SitoPubblico_EN/Navigation+Tree/Home/">Bocconi</a>
graduate from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trapani">Trapani</a>,
who has worked for other Rocket ventures in Australia
before landing here in Dubai: see, the amount of work he puts on,
the sleepless nights trying to improve workflows and metrics,
the fervent passion he shows (and the fun as well) on a daily basis
are very difficult to find elsewhere: it takes the right mix
of professionality and age, and I think Namshi makes it
exciting as people come to work to improve, learn and teach,
not (just) for their wage.</p>

<h2>Less talk, more action</h2>

<p><img class="left <a" src="href="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3683/11924594475_e884e51973.jpg">http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3683/11924594475_e884e51973.jpg</a>"></p>

<p>As Elvis sang<sup id='fnref:1'><a href='#fn:1' rel='footnote'>1</a></sup>, <strong>a little less conversation,
a little more action</strong>: holy words!</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re at a place where we don&rsquo;t rely too much on papers
but proactively experiment solutions (more on this later)
and reward those who make giant leaps with their actions.</p>

<p>It is also worth noting that we don&rsquo;t look <strong>too</strong> much at
experience if people have really the skills to become game changers
in the organization: I&rsquo;ve witnessed people without previous
experiences in teams becoming leaders among their peers.</p>

<p>Additionally, <strong>it&rsquo;s not your job title that defines your boundaries</strong>:
in the tech team, we&rsquo;ve had our most junior member writing and deploying
a NodeJS app in production with Capistrano<sup id='fnref:2'><a href='#fn:2' rel='footnote'>2</a></sup>.</p>

<p>Quoting <a href="ae.linkedin.com/in/sonjaneuber">Sonja</a>:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>[it matters] that people are really driven, that they are passionate about what they do; it doesn&rsquo;t matter that much how long they have worked in their jobs before, 15 years, 5 years, as long as they bring the right attitude and the right spirit on board</p><footer><strong>Sonja</strong> <cite>VP &ndash; Digital Marketing <a href="http://youtu.be/NThxiu1HGgM?t=3m1s">http://youtu.be/NThxiu1HGgM?t=3m1s</a> Working at Namshi</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<h2>MEMEs</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/meme-odino.jpg"></p>

<p>A modern startup cannot live without memes, it&rsquo;s phisically impossible:
here on the right you will find the one our team made for me,
to highlight my nature of late-night coder.</p>

<p>I find it amazing that we can gather together a bunch
of highly-skilled professional to build a dream and having
fun at the same time; having worked for other companies before
I can really say <strong>Namshi has the environment I enjoyed the most</strong>
so far.</p>

<h2>The family built by HR</h2>

<p>I must admit that HR played a <strong>huge role</strong> in making
Namshi an environment that gets better day after day:
the weekly internal newsletter, the
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/106891956@N06/sets/72157637043616496/">Namshi Olimpics</a>,
the <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/106891956@N06/sets/72157637897125985/">picnics</a>&hellip;</p>

<p>I never had the privilege to see these in any company
I&rsquo;ve worked for before<sup id='fnref:3'><a href='#fn:3' rel='footnote'>3</a></sup>.</p>

<h2>Technology stack</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;re a team of polyglots, as our SOA features 4 or 5 different
programming languages and we&rsquo;ve been using pretty interesting
systems over the past 2 years.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve started with refactoring a traditional
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multitier_architecture">n-tier</a>
architecture in order to be able to move towards a
Service Oriented Architecture while keeping up &amp; running
the existing services: the first steps were made with
Symfony2, and now we&rsquo;ve been throwing AngularJS and NodeJS
into the mix, while replacing memcache with Redis in order
to take advantage of a <strong>more structured key-value NoSQL
storage</strong>.</p>

<p>Things don&rsquo;t end on the <em>development</em> side: from the system point of you
we&rsquo;ve been using <a href="http://www.saltstack.com/">SaltStack</a> after a year of
<a href="http://puppetlabs.com/">Puppet</a> and are currently experimenting with
some tailor-made solutions for content delivery.</p>

<p>All in all, I must admit it feels damn exciting :)</p>

<h2>Ability to experiment</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/angularjs.png"></p>

<p>If you paid attention to the previous section, you have probably
noticed that we <strong>transitioned</strong> from an already decoupled architecture
(separate frontend and backend), which means that we had the
chance to experiment a lot in order to completely revamp it:
in the last 12 months we&rsquo;ve started using (for some of us
it was the first time ever) Symfony2, Redis, Lua, xDomain,
AngularJS, Grunt, HTTP extensions and JWS, not to mention the
traditional components of our stack, like RabbitMQ or Solr.</p>

<p>On top of this, we are now hungry for SPDY, WebP
and <strong>API orchestration layers</strong>.
More on this soon on this blog ;&ndash;)</p>

<h2>A great team of nerds</h2>

<p>I will never get bored of repeating this: the tech team, which
I&rsquo;m part of, <strong>feels like a family</strong>.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve seen some of us doing their first <code>composer.phar install</code>,
some saying &ldquo;<em>How do I f</em><em>**** get out of this?</em>&rdquo; after
opening VIM, some others reviewing my pull requests like a boss,
and others never hesitating to help a friend who
had his Vagrant machine stuck.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve seen the team growing into a squad able to deliver
enterprise applications under the motto
&ldquo;<a href="http://www.theverge.com/2013/8/14/4621378/the-facebook-ification-of-instagram-begins-today">move fast and break things</a>&rdquo;,
spending endless nights trying to fix PHPUnit tests or
rewriting a service in order to provide a robust checkout
experience written in JavaScript (JS, funky JS!).</p>

<p>Being part of this means recognizing that it will be very
difficult to replicate such achievements elsewhere,
something I will always be proud of.</p>

<h2>So?</h2>

<p>So yes, it feels good to be part of the Namshi family, and since
we have some <a href="/if-you-love-angularjs-you-should-definitely-join-us-dot-dot-dot-were-hiring/">open positions</a>
I would highly recommend you to give us a try :) Of course,
the world offers a lot of interesting and attractive
opportunities, but for the moment I must admit I still feel
<strong>very</strong> lucky.</p>

<p>Last but not least, I have to thank <a href="http://ae.linkedin.com/in/hosam">Hosam</a>,
<a href="http://ae.linkedin.com/in/farazkhalid">Faraz</a><sup id='fnref:4'><a href='#fn:4' rel='footnote'>4</a></sup> and
<a href="http://de.linkedin.com/in/hzarka">Hisham</a> for leading the
crazy family we enjoy on a daily basis!</p>

<p><em>All images courtesy of the <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/106891956@N06/">Namshi HR Flick stream</a></em></p>

<p><div class="footnotes">
<span>
Notes
</span>
	<ol>
		<li id='fn:1'>And a great remix can be found here: http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Zx1_6F-nCaw <a href='#fnref:1' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li><li id='fn:2'>They say 'sky is the limit', but in our case I would say 'your SSH key is the limit' <a href='#fnref:2' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li><li id='fn:3'>Albeit we had very crazy Christmas parties up there in Rome :) <a href='#fnref:3' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li><li id='fn:4'>When he doesn't wear his Google Glasses <a href='#fnref:4' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li>
	</ol>
</div>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[If you love AngularJS, you should definitely join us...we're hiring!]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.org/if-you-love-angularjs-you-should-definitely-join-us-dot-dot-dot-were-hiring/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-17T16:28:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.org/if-you-love-angularjs-you-should-definitely-join-us-dot-dot-dot-were-hiring</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In order to expand our team we are now looking for a
frontend JavaScript developer that loves Angular and wants to
drown under loads of <code>ng-*</code>, FPS optimizations and
building the frontends for our
<a href="/tips-and-tricks-for-you-service-oriented-architecture/">Service Oriented Architecture</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="right" src="/images/namshi.png"></p>

<p>If you are also interested in helping on the whole stack, here&rsquo;s a
summary of the rest of the technologies we&rsquo;re using down here at
<a href="http://namshi.com">Namshi</a>:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://symfony.com/">Symfony2</a></li>
<li><a href="http://nodejs.org/">NodeJS</a></li>
<li><a href="http://redis.io/">Redis</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.saltstack.com/">SaltStack</a></li>
<li><a href="http://angularjs.org/">AngularJS</a></li>
</ul>


<p>I must admit that is has been pretty exciting to get our
hands dirty with all of these (and the less attractive ones
as well :-P).</p>

<p>Dubai is a pretty nice place and we are <strong>very</strong> open
to relocations: if I&rsquo;m writing this blog post it&rsquo;s because
I would like to reach everyone on the internet who wants
to give it a shot, and not only our connections here in
Dubai.</p>

<p>Namshi is a <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NThxiu1HGgM">fun workplace</a>
and you&rsquo;re gonna be working with an
<a href="http://tech.namshi.com/portfolio/">highly skilled team</a>
with the goal of delivering the best customer experience in
the Middle East, through a website that should ideally
render in ~100ms, powered by lotsa APIs.</p>

<p>So yeah, what are you waiting for? <code>ng-apply</code> now!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Namshi is looking for a new Lead Developer!]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.org/namshi-is-looking-for-a-new-lead-developer/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-21T19:28:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.org/namshi-is-looking-for-a-new-lead-developer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As some of you know, I am currently employed by
<a href="http://en-ae.namshi.com/">Namshi</a>, a
<a href="http://www.rocket-internet.de/">Rocket Internet</a>
venture, here in Dubai, since almost a year: recently,
our CTO <a href="http://halilkoklu.de/">Halil</a> decided to move forward
and start a new adventure pretty far from here
so, as part of me taking care of other things than
development, we are looking for a new Lead Developer
who can strive, with the team, towards excellence.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>We are in the process of building new applications
and API to move towards a SOA architecture, using
cutting-edge libraries (like <a href="http://symfony.com/">Symfony2</a>), tools
(like <a href="http://behat.org/">Behat</a> and <a href="http://getcomposer.org/">Composer</a>) and practices.</p>

<p>The Job Description is still on his way but I can
post here some of the competencies that we are
looking forward to warmly welcome in the crazy Namshi
family:</p>

<ul>
<li>enterprise practices and patterns, such as automated testing, pair programming</li>
<li>HTTP webservices</li>
<li>you buzz around the PHP5.3+ ecosystem, from the Symfony2 components to tools such as Composer</li>
<li>you have Git for breakfast</li>
<li>RDBMS (MySQL, Percona)</li>
<li>can deal with pre-PHP5.3 frameworks (Zend 1 and Yii)</li>
<li>Solr and/or Memcached</li>
<li>passionate about open source and ideally contributing to it.</li>
</ul>


<p>The salary reflects the demand of skills that we are looking for, and
you will be responsible of the day-to-day development of our
applications.</p>

<p>Just to mention: the United Arab Emirated are a tax-free country,
the weather is amazing (even though for a couple months, during the summer,
its <strong>really</strong> hot) and it&rsquo;s an all-around country, meaning that if you
want, you can enjoy the glamorous side of Dubai or, if you dont feel like<sup id='fnref:1'><a href='#fn:1' rel='footnote'>1</a></sup>,
you can head towards the old town and enjoy the cultural meshup made
of Indonesia, Thai and Indian food or Arab heritage.</p>

<p>I rushed this post, I know, so you can ask for more informations
in the comments or, even better, drop me an email at
<em>alex.nadalin@namshi.com</em>.</p>

<p>Cheers!</p>

<p><div class="footnotes">
<span>
Notes
</span>
	<ol>
		<li id='fn:1'>Like me <a href='#fnref:1' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li>
	</ol>
</div>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
