<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: job | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="http://odino.org/blog/categories/job/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-01T14:23:29+04:00</updated>
  <id>http://odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Namshi is looking for a new Lead Developer!]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.org/namshi-is-looking-for-a-new-lead-developer/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-21T19:28:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.org/namshi-is-looking-for-a-new-lead-developer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As some of you know, I am currently employed by
<a href="http://en-ae.namshi.com/">Namshi</a>, a
<a href="http://www.rocket-internet.de/">Rocket Internet</a>
venture, here in Dubai, since almost a year: recently,
our CTO <a href="http://halilkoklu.de/">Halil</a> decided to move forward
and start a new adventure pretty far from here
so, as part of me taking care of other things than
development, we are looking for a new Lead Developer
who can strive, with the team, towards excellence.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>We are in the process of building new applications
and API to move towards a SOA architecture, using
cutting-edge libraries (like <a href="http://symfony.com/">Symfony2</a>), tools
(like <a href="http://behat.org/">Behat</a> and <a href="http://getcomposer.org/">Composer</a>) and practices.</p>

<p>The Job Description is still on his way but I can
post here some of the competencies that we are
looking forward to warmly welcome in the crazy Namshi
family:</p>

<ul>
<li>enterprise practices and patterns, such as automated testing, pair programming</li>
<li>HTTP webservices</li>
<li>you buzz around the PHP5.3+ ecosystem, from the Symfony2 components to tools such as Composer</li>
<li>you have Git for breakfast</li>
<li>RDBMS (MySQL, Percona)</li>
<li>can deal with pre-PHP5.3 frameworks (Zend 1 and Yii)</li>
<li>Solr and/or Memcached</li>
<li>passionate about open source and ideally contributing to it.</li>
</ul>


<p>The salary reflects the demand of skills that we are looking for, and
you will be responsible of the day-to-day development of our
applications.</p>

<p>Just to mention: the United Arab Emirated are a tax-free country,
the weather is amazing (even though for a couple months, during the summer,
its <strong>really</strong> hot) and it&rsquo;s an all-around country, meaning that if you
want, you can enjoy the glamorous side of Dubai or, if you dont feel like<sup id='fnref:1'><a href='#fn:1' rel='footnote'>1</a></sup>,
you can head towards the old town and enjoy the cultural meshup made
of Indonesia, Thai and Indian food or Arab heritage.</p>

<p>I rushed this post, I know, so you can ask for more informations
in the comments or, even better, drop me an email at
<em>alex.nadalin@namshi.com</em>.</p>

<p>Cheers!</p>

<p><div class="footnotes">
<span>
Notes
</span>
	<ol>
		<li id='fn:1'>Like me <a href='#fnref:1' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li>
	</ol>
</div>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
