<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Category: Web Security | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="https://odino.org/categories/web-security/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2022-05-07T15:04:41+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[WASEC, a Book About Web Application Security, Is Now Available for Sale]]></title>
    <link href="https://odino.org/wasec-a-book-about-web-application-security-is-now-available-for-sale/"/>
    <updated>2019-11-25T22:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://odino.org/wasec-a-book-about-web-application-security-is-now-available-for-sale</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/wasec.jpeg"></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m pleased to announce (even though you might have already heard about this on <a href="https://twitter.com/_odino_">my Twitter stream</a>)
that the ebook on web application security I&rsquo;ve been working on over the past year is now
officially available for sale, at the hopefully-reasonable price of <del>$6.99</del> $9.99.</p>

<p>You can now buy the book at <a href="https://leanpub.com/wasec">leanpub.com/wasec</a>, while Kindle enthusiasts will
have to wait a few more days for it to become available there: it is currently available for <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B081Z7SD48">pre-order</a>
and should be generally available in the next few days.</p>

<p>WASEC is the culmination of over a year of thoughts regarding my experience with web application
security from the point of view of a software engineer, rather than the one of a security researcher.
I believe software engineers might find it extremely interesting as it approaches <em>defensive</em> security
from the point of view of someone who has to build an app and needs to keep security into consideration
<em>among other things</em>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>If you&rsquo;re unsure about purchasing the ebook you can take a look at some of its content that I previously
shared <a href="/introduction-to-web-application-security/">in this blog</a>. If reading lengthy blog posts isn&rsquo;t
your thing, you can also download the sample version from <a href="https://leanpub.com/wasec">leanpub itself</a> &mdash; it contains the first few
complete chapters of the book.</p>

<h2>What if I can&rsquo;t afford the book?</h2>

<p>Reach out to me privately, and we&rsquo;ll sort something out. I will need to make sure you&rsquo;re not trying
to <em>gamble the system</em>, but I&rsquo;d hate to see someone not being able to read the book simply because they
can&rsquo;t afford it &mdash; I will try to make an effort to reply to everyone who reaches out to me, and make sure
financial conditions don&rsquo;t get in the way of knowledge.</p>

<p>I wrote this book to share what my experience with
web security has been and, frankly, I don&rsquo;t think I&rsquo;ll ever make the money I spent on it (in terms of man-hours)
ever &mdash; so there&rsquo;s no point in being greedy :&ndash;)</p>

<p>Again, ping me and we&rsquo;ll try to work something out.</p>

<h2>Sayonara</h2>

<p>Again, please make sure you visit <a href="https://leanpub.com/wasec">WASEC&rsquo;s book page on leanpub</a> and,
if you&rsquo;re interested in the topic and have a few bucks to spare, buy the book. Leanpub has a 45-day &ldquo;<a href="http://help.leanpub.com/en/articles/110743-what-if-i-want-to-return-a-book-can-i-get-a-refund">100% Happiness Guarantee</a>&rdquo;,
which means there&rsquo;s no risk in purchasing any Leanpub book, and they make it easy to get a refund if you&rsquo;ve tried
a book and want your money back within 45 days of your purchase. If you end up reading the book, feel free to reach
out and let me know what your thoughts are.</p>

<p>In the next few days I&rsquo;ll be publishing some more updates to the book (all future updates will be available for
free for users who have purchased it) and release it on the Kindle store &mdash; hit me up if you have any question.</p>

<p>Adios!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>