<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Category: Cncf | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="https://odino.org/categories/cncf/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2021-07-18T10:30:41+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: Cloud Native Infrastructure]]></title>
    <link href="https://odino.org/book-review-cloud-native-infrastructure/"/>
    <updated>2018-09-01T12:25:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://odino.org/book-review-cloud-native-infrastructure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/cni-book.jpg"></p>

<p>This goes right into the list of <a href="/book-review-nodejs-high-performance/">books I really wanted to like</a> but kind of
disappointed me.</p>

<p>The book is structured extremely well, so it comes out as a very enjoyable read.
One downside, though, becomes fairly evident a few chapters in:
it isn&rsquo;t practical at all, describes few patterns and instead focuses a lot
on processes, advices and high-level description of approaches you should follow
to embrace CN infrastructure.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I was probably expecting too much, but when I read the book&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Cloud-Native-Infrastructure-Applications-Environment/dp/1491984309">description on the
Kindle store</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>This <strong>practical</strong> guide shows you how to design and maintain infrastructure capable of managing the full lifecycle of these implementations.</p></blockquote>

<p>I got fairly excited and proceeded to buy.</p>

<p>Again, as I mentioned the book is really nice to read &mdash; I devoured it during my
daily commute to work, and that&rsquo;s something you don&rsquo;t expect from most technical books.
When it comes to content, though, I found it a tad repetitive and without many
real-world examples / lessons, so it felt more of an &ldquo;abstract&rdquo; book around
the Cloud Native ecosystem than anything else.</p>

<p>I would have definitely appreciated
if the last chapter, which serves as an introduction to interesting patterns
such as circuit breaking, would have gone more into details: it might have been
out of the scope of the book but would have definitely made it feel more &ldquo;hands-on&rdquo;.</p>

<p>At the end of the day, Cloud Native infrastructure goes down as an introductory
guide to the CN world. I’d recommend you to read it if you just started
approaching the ecosystem.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>