<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: PUG | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="http://odino.github.io/blog/categories/pug/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://odino.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-18T13:59:12+04:00</updated>
  <id>http://odino.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PHP User Group Dubai, here we start again!]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.github.io/php-user-group-dubai-here-we-start-again/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-18T13:38:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.github.io/php-user-group-dubai-here-we-start-again</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After launching a couple
PHP User Groups in Italy
(<a href="http://roma.grusp.org">Rome</a> and <a href="http://friuli.grusp.org">Friuli</a>),
I started to feel kind of lost here in
Dubai, a place that gathers together lots
of talents but doesn&rsquo;t have that much of
knowledge-sharing culture.</p>

<p>Given this and the pro-active involvement of
some of my colleagues from <a href="http://en-ae.namshi.com">Namshi</a>,
I really wanted to see some sort of community
raise in this desert.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So a couple weeks ago I opened a
<a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#!forum/php-user-group-dubai">google group</a>
for the PHP User Group Dubai &ndash; pretty empty right now &ndash; which is the place
where we&rsquo;re going to discuss meetings, ask for support
and <em>chillax</em> in a nerdy way.</p>

<p>Yesterday we had our first meeting, where 7 of us
discussed on the directions that we should initially take to gain the attention of others in the development community and
which kind of formats to use during our meetings; the main points that came out of the meeting are:</p>

<ul>
<li>we will try to meet once a month</li>
<li>we will try to set and prepare the next meeting before the beginning of Ramadan (~10 July)</li>
<li>everyone will try to bring a new joiner (friend, colleague, etc.) to the next meeting</li>
<li>we will have a talk and a discussion after that, most probably in front of a dinner accompanied by some <em>sheesha</em></li>
<li>most probably, since not everyone is aware of the potential and benefits of automated testing, we will prepare a talk on
PHPUnit</li>
</ul>


<p>So, if you are a PHP developer based in the UAE
&ndash; not necessarily Dubai &ndash; why don&rsquo;t you subscribe
to our <a href="groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups#!forum/php-user-group-dubai">PHP User Group Dubai google group</a> and
introduce yourself? Do you want to understand why testing your applications manually it&rsquo;s a waste of your energies and of money of your company? Do you know about <a href="http://twig.sensiolabs.org">Twig</a>? Have you ever tried developing an application with <a href="http://angularjs.org/">AngularJS</a> and some HTTP APIs as the backend of that app? How can you <a href="/securing-your-http-api-with-javascript-object-signing-and-encryption/">integrate the JWS authentication mechanism in your PHP code</a>?</p>

<p>It would be great to see you at the next meeting!<sup id='fnref:1'><a href='#fn:1' rel='footnote'>1</a></sup></p>

<p><div class="footnotes">
<span>
Notes
</span>
	<ol>
		<li id='fn:1'>By the way, we will decide the date, location and topic of the meeting with a discussion in the google group <a href='#fnref:1' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li>
	</ol>
</div>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
