<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Category: Blog | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="https://odino.org/categories/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2021-07-25T08:48:47+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cross-posting on Medium]]></title>
    <link href="https://odino.org/cross-posting-on-medium/"/>
    <updated>2017-12-29T15:43:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://odino.org/cross-posting-on-medium</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just a heads up: I&rsquo;ve decided to follow <a href="https://twitter.com/cirpo">a friend</a>&rsquo;s
advice and start cross-posting the contents of this blog on <a href="https://medium.com/">Medium</a>.</p>

<p>All new content will be published both here (I like my data!) and there, with the
goal of reaching a broader community. I also got fed up with the Disqus comments
(they mostly show freaking clickbait links) and wanted to find an alternative, so
I will be shutting down comments on my blog shortly and instead point people to
Medium.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s <a href="https://medium.com/@alexnadalin">my profile</a> and a link to my latest
<a href="https://medium.com/@alexnadalin/unix-goodies-to-the-rescue-vol-2-5da643407561">medium-ized post</a> :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The 2017 Blogging Pledge]]></title>
    <link href="https://odino.org/the-2017-blogging-pledge/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-02T16:54:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://odino.org/the-2017-blogging-pledge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last year I wrote <a href="/archives">12 posts</a>, which makes it
a decent average of once a month.</p>

<p>Even though I would have liked to be able to blog more
often (and do some more public coding: there are at least
&frac34; projects I have worked on without getting them far enough
to make it to github), I&rsquo;m still happy
with the outcome so far &mdash; at the end of the day this
blog still attracts a few hundred visitors a day and
I&rsquo;m happy as long as I retain those numbers.</p>

<p>For 2017 I would like, though, to follow a different
approach while try to put in the same amount of effort,
with &ndash; hopefully &ndash; better results.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>One post a month is generally easy to achieve, especially
when you aim low and publish very short pieces (<a href="http://odino.org/xyz-programming-language-sucks/">BUSTED!</a>),
something I want to change by working with a different
approach:</p>

<ul>
<li>still try to publish 1 post a month (let&rsquo;s be realistic), with exceptions if there are some quick articles I&rsquo;d like to share</li>
<li>pick a broad topic (ie. resiliency in distributed systems)</li>
<li>start working on a &ldquo;schedule&rdquo; at the beginning of the month, thinking what I want to cover, examples, caveats, etc so that the post is as exhaustive as possible (something like <a href="https://hackernoon.com/10-things-i-learned-making-the-fastest-site-in-the-world-18a0e1cdf4a7#.ucqcvhqyi">this</a>)</li>
<li>publish the article by the end of the month</li>
</ul>


<p>I have noted down the list of posts I would like to blog about
in the <a href="/archives/">archives section of the blog</a>, so you can always get an
idea of what I&rsquo;m working on &mdash; hopefully this year I will be
able to deliver more in-depth, exhaustive, well-thought articles
to my (few) readers.</p>

<p>See ya!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>