<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Category: Github | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="http://odino.org/blog/categories/github/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-06T11:03:50+04:00</updated>
  <id>http://odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Source Code Workflow After 3 Months of Github]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.org/source-code-workflow-after-3-months-of-github/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-05T23:16:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.org/source-code-workflow-after-3-months-of-github</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I joined <em>Rocket Internet</em> 4 months ago,
here in Dubai, the team was about to experience
the transition from the very old SVN to Git, with
everything hosted on <a href="https://github.com">Github</a>.</p>

<p>In this post I try to wrap-up the impressions
of the team and the changes in the lifecycle of
our source code with the adoption of the
Git+Github combo.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="right" src="/images/github.png"></p>

<h2>Premise</h2>

<p>We had our first meeting about the switch to Git
after our CTO migrated our repositories from
our hosted SVN repos to Github with
<a href="http://www.kernel.org/pub/software/scm/git/docs/git-svn.html">git-svn</a>.</p>

<p>In that meeting &ndash; useful for a lot of people who
never used Git before &ndash; we explained the basic
stuff that you should know to get started with
this VCS:</p>

<ul>
<li>distribute vs centralized versioning system</li>
<li>Github act as a remote</li>
<li><code>commit</code> is local</li>
<li><code>push</code>, <code>pull</code> and <code>fetch</code></li>
<li>rebasing</li>
<li>branching and merging</li>
<li><a href="http://nvie.com/posts/a-successful-git-branching-model/">gitflow</a></li>
</ul>


<p>All in all we wanted to follow gitflow but at the
end it turned out that in some parts we had to simplify
the workflow and add more complexity somewhere else:
keep reading to get more insights.</p>

<h2>Our development workflow</h2>

<p>So let&rsquo;s say that today we have <code>master</code> and <code>dev</code> aligned:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>master</code> is an <em>always-ready-to-be-released</em> branch, in which
you commit code that is tested and works on production: the aim is
to have a solid fallback if you deploy and need to rollback ( <a href="https://github.com/capistrano/capistrano/wiki/">capistrano</a>
would probably be a better solution, since it&rsquo;s more immediate, but
again you need an history of working versions )</li>
<li><code>dev</code> branches from <code>master</code>: it&rsquo;s the integration branch, where
you merge features developed for your next release</li>
</ul>


<p>As the days go by, people will branch from develop to
implement new features/fix bugs:</p>

<p><code>bash
git checkout develop
git checkout -b bug-1123
</code></p>

<p>The developer is free to handle its <em>ticket</em> with both
local and remote branches: although pushing to the remote
makes <a href="http://ariejan.net/2011/07/05/git-squash-your-latests-commits-into-one/">squashing</a> harder, I would always recommend to push
every day.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s say that the bugfixing seems done and we are ready
to include that code in the <code>develop</code>, which is gonna lead
to our next release: the developer now opens a <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/using-pull-requests/">pull request</a>
from its branch to <code>develop</code>:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/pull-request.jpeg"></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s always useful to name the PR like <code>TICKET-ID Headline</code>
and add a few more comments to explain your changes, if it&rsquo;s worth it:
given that you <strong>name your branches after the tickets</strong> that they
implement/fix, adding the ticket ID to the PR&rsquo;s title lets
who needs to merge it into develop to directly copy the branch
name from Github &ndash; otherwise you need to type it manully<sup id='fnref:2'><a href='#fn:2' rel='footnote'>2</a></sup>.</p>

<p>The release manager ( who reviews PRs and merges them into
the integration branch ) can now have a look at your PR,
comment it and accept or reject it:</p>

<ul>
<li>if it&rsquo;s accepted it gets merged and the ticket status
changes from <code>bugfixing</code><sup id='fnref:1'><a href='#fn:1' rel='footnote'>1</a></sup> to <code>Ready for QA</code></li>
<li>if rejected it&rsquo;s re-assigned back to the developer, and
technical comments are added <strong>directly on Github</strong></li>
</ul>


<p><code>bash After the release manager has positively evaluated your PR, ctrl+c on the branch name...
git fetch
git checkout TICKET-ID
git checkout develop
git merge --no-ff TICKET-ID
</code></p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/pull-request-namshi.png"></p>

<p>Now times has come to go live with a set of changes:
a <strong>release branch</strong> is created and we tag version
<code>X.Y.Z-beta1</code>, that is gonna be deployed in the first
development environment ( sort of pre-staging ).</p>

<p>If some tests are not passing, the developers add the
related fixes and open the PRs in the release branch
( <code>release-X.Y.Z</code> ), so we re-tag and redeploy ( <code>X.Y.Z-beta2</code> ):
if someone is working on other tickets, which don&rsquo;t have to
be included in version <code>X.Y.Z</code>, the integration branch
is still <code>develop</code>.</p>

<p>After this, a new tag <code>X.Y.Z-rc1</code> is deployed into the
staging environment: if everything is good we create a
new tag, <code>X.Y.Z</code> and go live with it.</p>

<p>After a few hours, we can consider this tag <strong>valid</strong>
and update both <code>master</code> and <code>develop</code>:</p>

<p><code>bash
git checkout master
git merge --no-ff X.Y.Z
git push origin master
git checkout develop
git rebase master
git push -f origin develop
</code></p>

<p>The development cycle starts again.</p>

<h2>Critical paths</h2>

<p>There are some problematic aspects to consider when
you are working with almost 10 people daily pushing/pulling
from the same remote:</p>

<ul>
<li>when you rebase <code>develop</code>, pull request can include old commits
that are already merged, so you just need to ask for a rebase of the
PR&rsquo;s branch</li>
<li>when you rebase <code>develop</code>, always ask people to pull the remote
develop in their local ones, otherwise they will be working with a
different tree ( after the rebase Git is not smart enough to
connect the pre-rebase and after-rebase trees )</li>
<li>if you need to do an hotfix deployment, always branch from
<code>master</code> or the release branch ( if the related tag wasn&rsquo;t merged into
<code>master</code> ): you don&rsquo;t want to <code>cherry-pick</code> commits and then
manually update the PR which takes care of the hotfix</li>
</ul>


<h2>Conclusions</h2>

<p>All in all I think our process has improved so much: first of all
we see less conflicts, thanks to the Git engine<sup id='fnref:3'><a href='#fn:3' rel='footnote'>3</a></sup>, second we have more <strong>control,
transparency and visibility</strong> towards code: being able to comment
every single line of code on Github really helps you when you need
to handle several PRs at once; not to mention the fact that doing
<strong>release-management is way easier</strong>.</p>

<p>By the way, pull request are another good stage of the workflow, since
they let the developer take a final look at the code, review it for
the last time and explain it in the PR message, something that with
SVN and SVN-based services ( like GH ) was <strong>nearly impossible</strong>.</p>

<p>Additionally, coming from Atlassian&rsquo;s hosted services, Github gives
you the reliability I always missed: no apparent downtime so far
and pulling/pushing is really fast; compared to SVN,
this is a huge win for us.</p>

<p>At the end I&rsquo;d say that <strong>we almost doubled our potential</strong> with
these changes, and I think it&rsquo;s 50% because of Git and another 50%
&lsquo;cause of Github: if you don&rsquo;t use them, I definitely recommend
you to switch as soon as possible<sup id='fnref:4'><a href='#fn:4' rel='footnote'>4</a></sup>.</p>

<p><div class="footnotes">
<span>
Notes
</span>
	<ol>
		<li id='fn:1'>We use &lsquo;bigfixing&rsquo; both for new features and bugs, it&rsquo;s just to identify a status in which the developer is working on the ticket <a href='#fnref:1' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li><li id='fn:2'>Github&rsquo;s markup makes it difficult to <code>ctrl+c</code> it from the &ldquo;You&rsquo;re asking @user to merge 1 commit into repo:develop from repo:TICKET-ID&rdquo; string <a href='#fnref:2' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li><li id='fn:3'>But this can just be just my personal feeling <a href='#fnref:3' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li><li id='fn:4'>BitBucket is a pretty cheap alternative to Github <a href='#fnref:4' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li>
	</ol>
</div>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bootstrap of a Travis-CI Test-machine]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.org/bootstrap-of-a-travis-ci-test-machine/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-27T07:00:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.org/bootstrap-of-a-travis-ci-test-machine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://travis-ci.org/">Travis-CI</a> is an awesome open source service which
makes continuos integration really easy in the context
of <em>github-hosted</em> projects.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Developing Orient, I found out about Travis when one of
the 3 active guys actively collaborating to the project,
<a href="https://github.com/nrk">Daniele</a> created his own fork of the library to create
the CI environment on Travis.</p>

<h2>More than testing</h2>

<p>Travis doesn&rsquo;t only provide a machine in which you can
continuosly running tests, it gives you a <strong>free</strong> VM
which you can <strong>freely</strong> manage in the context of testing
an application: although they don&rsquo;t actually give you a &ldquo;real&rdquo; VM, they provide
you an <strong>temporary VM</strong> which gets bootstrapped following
your indications and executes the tasks that <strong>you</strong>
indicate: in that sense, Travis gives you VMs
<em>on-demand</em>.</p>

<p>So think about it: it&rsquo;s not only about testing, it&rsquo;s about
having an environment ready to do anything you want for
your own project, like running reports.</p>

<h2>A real world example</h2>

<p>For <a href="http://github.com/congow/Orient">Orient</a>, Daniele managed to setup a quite clever
bootstrap script.</p>

<p>We have a quite comprehensive test-suite which you can
execute with the single <code>phpunit</code> command, from the root
of the library, but it just executes tests which dont
directly talk to OrientDB.</p>

<p>To execute the full test-suite, including integration
tests, you just need to pass the test directory to the
CLI:</p>

<p><code>php
phpunit test/
</code></p>

<p>but you&rsquo;ll need a working instance of OrientDB, with
predefined admin credentials (<code>admin</code>/<code>admin</code>) listening
on port <code>:2480</code>.</p>

<p>So our challenge was to use Travis and being able to trigger
the integration tests.</p>

<p>In the <code>.travis.yml</code> configuration file, we have:</p>

<p>```
language: php
php:
  &ndash; 5.3
  &ndash; 5.4
before_script:
  &ndash; sh -c ./bin/initialize-ci.sh 1.0rc6
script: phpunit test/
notifications:
  email:</p>

<pre><code>- ...@gmail.com
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>So, as you see, we have a bash script which
takes care of everything:</p>

<p>``` bash ./bin/initialize-ci.sh 1.0rc6</p>

<h1>!/bin/sh</h1>

<p>PARENT_DIR=$(dirname $(cd &ldquo;$(dirname &rdquo;$0")&ldquo;; pwd))
CI_DIR=&rdquo;$PARENT_DIR/ci-stuff/environment"</p>

<p>ODB_VERSION=${1:&ndash;&ldquo;1.0rc6&rdquo;}
ODB_PACKAGE=&ldquo;orientdb-${ODB_VERSION}&rdquo;
ODB_DIR=&ldquo;${CI_DIR}/${ODB_PACKAGE}&rdquo;
ODB_LAUNCHER=&ldquo;${ODB_DIR}/bin/server.sh&rdquo;</p>

<p>echo &ldquo;=== Initializing CI environment ===&rdquo;</p>

<p>cd &ldquo;$PARENT_DIR&rdquo;</p>

<p>. &ldquo;$PARENT_DIR/bin/odb-shared.sh&rdquo;</p>

<p>if [ ! -d &ldquo;$CI_DIR&rdquo; ]; then
  # Fetch the stuff needed to run the CI session.
  git clone &mdash;quiet git://gist.github.com/1370152.git $CI_DIR</p>

<p>  # Download and extract OrientDB
  echo &ldquo;&mdash;&ndash; Downloading OrientDB v${ODB_VERSION} &mdash;&ndash;&rdquo;
  odb_download &ldquo;<a href="http://orient.googlecode.com/files/$">http://orient.googlecode.com/files/$</a>{ODB_PACKAGE}.zip&rdquo; $CI_DIR
  unzip -q &ldquo;${CI_DIR}/${ODB_PACKAGE}.zip&rdquo; -d $ODB_DIR &amp;&amp; chmod +x $ODB_LAUNCHER</p>

<p>  # Copy the configuration file and the demo database
  echo &ldquo;&mdash;&ndash; Setting up OrientDB &mdash;&ndash;&rdquo;
  tar xf $CI_DIR/databases.tar.gz -C &ldquo;${ODB_DIR}/&rdquo;
  cp $PARENT_DIR/ci-stuff/orientdb-server-config.xml &ldquo;${ODB_DIR}/config/&rdquo;
  cp $PARENT_DIR/ci-stuff/orientdb-server-log.properties &ldquo;${ODB_DIR}/config/&rdquo;
else
  echo &ldquo;!!! Directory $CI_DIR exists, skipping downloads !!!&rdquo;
fi</p>

<h1>Start OrientDB in background.</h1>

<p>echo &ldquo;&mdash;&ndash; Starting an instance of OrientDB &mdash;&ndash;&rdquo;
sh -c $ODB_LAUNCHER </dev/null &>/dev/null &amp;</p>

<h1>Wait a bit for OrientDB to finish the initialization phase.</h1>

<p>sleep 5
printf &ldquo;\n=== The CI environment has been initialized ===\n&rdquo;
```</p>

<p>I think the script speaks for itsef: we directly download
OrientDB from the official website, de-compress it, configure
OrientDB with our standard configuration file and launch the
ODB server, outputting in <code>/dev/null</code>.</p>

<p>Now, all of this happens everytime someone commits to the <code>master</code>
on Github: pretty easy, simple but so powerful.</p>

<p>I really recommend you to start having a look at Travi-CI
and how you can benefit from a CI server, fully configurable,
for free, for the sake of your own code.</p>

<p>One last note: yes, all of this comes for free, but if you use
Travis you should really consider making a donation to
show the guys behind the project <a href="http://love.travis-ci.org/">your love</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>