<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Category: Cs | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="https://odino.org/categories/cs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2021-07-18T10:30:41+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: Computing, a Coincise History]]></title>
    <link href="https://odino.org/book-review-computing-a-coincise-history/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-16T14:25:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://odino.org/book-review-computing-a-coincise-history</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>New book review &mdash; getting tired?</p>

<p>This time I wanted to know a little bit more
about the history of computing, but didn&rsquo;t want to spend too much time on it,
thus I decided to give <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Computing-Concise-History-Essential-Knowledge/dp/0262517671">Computing: A Concise History</a> a go.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="right" src="/images/book-computing.jpg"></p>

<p>The book is honestly <em>ok</em>, meaning you can definitely live without reading it:
it&rsquo;s surely a good wrap-up on the history of computing, but I can&rsquo;t really say
I was extremely happy by the time I finished it.</p>

<p>At the end of the day, though, I need to also consider that the author wanted
to give a very brief (hence the word <em>coincise</em>) overview of the matter, so it&rsquo;s natural
the book doesn&rsquo;t dig deep into the topic. Overall, I think it&rsquo;s an interesting
read to go back to when you want to discuss the subject with others, but you won&rsquo;t
really find hidden gems in here.</p>

<p>One thing that I really didn&rsquo;t like is that there are very few
mind-blowing stories: the history of computing probably has an incredible
amount of funny or interesting anectodes, but you won&rsquo;t find many of them here.
Faithful to its title, the book describes how computing evolved, from war machines
to the internet, assuming that the reader doesn&rsquo;t have too much time to waste;
in that sense it definitely delivers on its premise.</p>

<p>Like we use to say in italy: <em><a href="https://forum.wordreference.com/threads/senza-lode-senza-infamia.620099/">no praise, no blame</a></em>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>