<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Category: Personal | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="https://odino.org/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2022-02-21T09:37:30+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Last Day at Namshi: Goodbye Folks!]]></title>
    <link href="https://odino.org/goodbye-namshi/"/>
    <updated>2019-09-15T19:42:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://odino.org/goodbye-namshi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, I wave goodbye to the company I supported for the past 7 and
a half years, Namshi.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It&rsquo;s with mixed feeling that I write this blog post, as it&rsquo;s been
a hell of a ride and I recognize I was privileged to get on board
just at the right time. It is a truly
bittersweet moment to leave behind something you&rsquo;ve dedicate so much
to, but I do feel <em>my time is now</em>: after all of these years I long for a change
of scenery, (somewhat) different challenges and new environment
to flourish in. It won&rsquo;t be easy to replicate what we&rsquo;ve done over
the past years, but the least I can do is to try to spread all the
good I&rsquo;ve experienced.</p>

<p>To all my teammates, I thank you for striving to make this
happen: we wouldn&rsquo;t have come anywhere near to where we are right now
if it wasn&rsquo;t for the collective team effort we put over the years.
This is a &ldquo;thank you&rdquo; that spans 7 years of life, so it goes to the
the current team as much as it goes to the ones who were there in
2012, when it was real wild. From the warehouse to HQ, your work
was impressive, and it&rsquo;s a great story in the region.</p>

<p>I want to take a moment to mention <a href="https://tech.namshi.io/team/">the folks
in the tech team</a>, as their loyalty and
effort have ignited my days for years &mdash; if it wasn&rsquo;t for what
my teammates have been putting in day in and day out, I don&rsquo;t think
I could have lasted this long.</p>

<p>Among all of the positive qualities that this tech team developed,
there&rsquo;s one I want to call out: the <strong>generosity</strong> that is embedded in this team&rsquo;s
DNA is what is going to make me proud for years to come, as how much
each and every individual strives to help their teammates is something
I haven&rsquo;t experienced before. I am truly happy to say that
we are a team of great software engineers but, way before that,
great human beings.</p>

<p>As for myself, I will take a break, and focus on the next crazy ride
right after. I&rsquo;m not planning to get back to work for at least another couple
of months, and I haven&rsquo;t finalized anything yet. What I can say, though,
is that I&rsquo;m not planning to sit down and discuss new opportunities as I&rsquo;ve
already done that and have shortlisted my options. I&rsquo;m excited about this
ambiguity and, more importantly, I&rsquo;m excited about spending my next
couple of months relaxing, recharging my batteries and waiting to see
the future unfold in front of me.</p>

<p>Bye folks, it&rsquo;s been a pleasure.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Married!]]></title>
    <link href="https://odino.org/married/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-15T03:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://odino.org/married</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/wedding.jpg"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[3 Years at Namshi... And Still Counting!]]></title>
    <link href="https://odino.org/3-years-at-namshi-dot-dot-dot-and-still-counting/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-01T22:20:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://odino.org/3-years-at-namshi-dot-dot-dot-and-still-counting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I celebrate my third birthday at Namshi, 3 long, long
years that represent an amazing journey in my life.</p>

<p>There are so many moments I will remember forever, many positive ones,
few negative ones, a lot of excitement and huge growth, both
from a personal and professional perspective. There are very
few things I regret and I&rsquo;m honestly proud of that.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>There is one big <strong>thank you</strong> that goes to the people in our
team<sup id='fnref:1'><a href='#fn:1' rel='footnote'>1</a></sup>. These guys, their
passion, willingness and fighting spirit are what makes the
tech room a sweet home for me.</p>

<p>Instead of mentioning these crazy freaks, I&rsquo;d like to look
back at the moments we spent together, wishing everone
to spend more time with each other in the years to come.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/3yn-1.png">
<img class="center" src="/images/3yn-2.png">
<img class="center" src="/images/3yn-3.png">
<img class="center" src="/images/3yn-5.png">
<img class="center" src="/images/3yn-6.png">
<img class="center" src="/images/3yn-7.png">
<img class="center" src="/images/3yn-8.png">
<img class="center" src="/images/3yn-9.png">
<img class="center" src="/images/3yn-10.png">
<img class="center" src="/images/3yn-11.png">
<img class="center" src="/images/3yn-12.png">
<img class="center" src="/images/3yn-13.png"></p>

<p>Hopefully, in a few years, I will have many more pictures
to add here :)</p>

<p><div class="footnotes">
<span>
Notes
</span>
	<ol>
		<li id='fn:1'>should thank many more across the board, but then this post would become a grocery shopping list :) <a href='#fnref:1' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li>
	</ol>
</div>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Victory]]></title>
    <link href="https://odino.org/victory/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-10T13:45:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://odino.org/victory</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="/netflix-you-have-a-problem/">long battle</a> is over :)</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/netflix-cancellation.png"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Netflix, You Have a Problem]]></title>
    <link href="https://odino.org/netflix-you-have-a-problem/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-14T20:43:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://odino.org/netflix-you-have-a-problem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the story of how Netflix is really
trying to be funny&hellip;no, super-funny!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I&rsquo;ve ran a Netflix account for quite some
time but, after moving from Rome to Dubai
I stopped using the service as it would mean
using a VPN and stuff like that which is quite
against my principle of keeping things simple.</p>

<p>In the past months, while checking the statements
from my italian bank, I noticed that Netflix
kept billing me (cool), so I decided to try unsubscribing
from here, which turned out to be impossible.</p>

<p>Since I forgot my password, I tried recovering it:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/netflix-password-recovery.png"></p>

<p>Ok, no worries &mdash; it might be that I used another email!</p>

<p>A quick look into my inbox revealed that I was
going to face hard times:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/netflix-joining.png"></p>

<p>I used my regular email but still, Netflix
was refusing to let me in from their global
website. Could it be that their customer DB is
a bit messed up? Maybe if I go for the social
login I&rsquo;ll be able to get into my account:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/facebook-netflix.png"></p>

<p>Should have never tried this one, ya? It amazes me
how they cannot even provide complete error
messages.</p>

<p>So here I am, unable to unsubscribe from a service
I am not using anymore; the only reasonable thing
was to try reaching out to these guys and ask them
what to do: I did that <a href="https://twitter.com/_odino_/status/468734390537687040">once</a>,
then a <a href="https://twitter.com/_odino_/status/465149059691339776">second time</a> and,
just to be sure, I tried it <a href="https://twitter.com/_odino_/status/528982644688564225">a couple months ago</a> as well.</p>

<p>All attempts went unheard: it was clear by now that
<strong>Netflix didn&rsquo;t really seem to care that much</strong>.</p>

<p>Luckily, the credit card I used to sign up expired
this month and Netflix could not charge me anymore.</p>

<p>That meant receiving one of the most sarcastic emails
ever:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/netflix.png"></p>

<p>No, Netflix, <strong>you</strong> have a problem.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>