<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Category: Battery Life | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="https://odino.org/categories/battery-life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2021-07-24T08:15:36+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Something Strange Happened to My Laptop's Battery]]></title>
    <link href="https://odino.org/something-strange-happened-to-my-laptops-battery/"/>
    <updated>2018-11-30T17:48:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://odino.org/something-strange-happened-to-my-laptops-battery</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago I got to the office and noticed something
peculiar: my XPS' battery had around 7 remaining hours
of life, while until the week earlier I had never seen it above 3 hours.</p>

<p>This is the (very short) story of how I supercharged my
laptop&rsquo;s battery without even knowing how to.</p>

<!-- more-->


<h2>A bit of background</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/laptop-charge-1.png"></p>

<p>Last month I flew to the most beautiful continent in
the world with the idea of spending a whole week doing safaris in
<a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=serengeti&amp;source=lnms&amp;tbm=isch&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiW9JXVqf_eAhWJ_lQKHYGgCYsQ_AUIDygC&amp;biw=1920&amp;bih=990">Tanzania&rsquo;s national parks</a>.</p>

<p>Suffice to say I wasn&rsquo;t super excited about bringing
my laptop with me, mainly because:</p>

<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;d be on a jeep the whole time, and carrying it with me would
make no sense, since I&rsquo;d just put it under a lot of stress</li>
<li>I spent most of my nights at a camp that did not have any
internet access at all, so good luck getting online regardless</li>
</ul>


<p>Eventually, I decided to leave the laptop at home, something
I hadn&rsquo;t done since a few years. Gone for a good week&hellip;</p>

<p>Once I got home, I noticed something interesting:
the light that signals the battery level is low was blinking &mdash;
&ldquo;probably got drained over the week&rdquo;, I thought.</p>

<p>Plugged in my charger, waited until the laptop was fully
charged, then the miracle happened: since then,
the battery life has been extended by &frac34; hours at least
(you might think that&rsquo;s not crazy, but for a battery that
used to give me &frac34; hours of love at most, being able to do 6/8 hours
in a row is a blessing).</p>

<h2>How did this happen?</h2>

<p>Frankly, I do not know. I&rsquo;ve always been a big believer of letting the
battery work &ldquo;at full capacity&rdquo;, meaning that I let it drain as much as
possible before charging it until it&rsquo;s completely full.</p>

<p>I think this week-long draining session, without small charges
in between, has allowed the battery to calibrate (?) better,
or <em>god-knows-what</em>. Right now, being left with 20% of battery
means I can still go on for a couple of hours:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/laptop-charge.png"></p>

<p>All I know is that I have a better battery<sup id='fnref:1'><a href='#fn:1' rel='footnote'>1</a></sup>, and I owe it to
going on a vacation and being able to &ldquo;disconnect&rdquo;. Probably, the underlying lesson is that it&rsquo;s good to disconnect once a year :)</p>

<p>Adios!</p>

<p><div class="footnotes">
<span>
Notes
</span>
	<ol>
		<li id='fn:1'>Critics will argue that the battery life should generally trend north of 8h (https://www.google.com/search?q=dell+xps+battery+life&amp;oq=dell+xps+battery+life&amp;aqs=chrome..69i57j0l5.2957j0j7&amp;sourceid=chrome&amp;ie=UTF-8), but let's be realistic... <a href='#fnref:1' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li>
	</ol>
</div>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>