<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: conference | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="http://odino.org/blog/categories/conference/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-28T14:42:09+04:00</updated>
  <id>http://odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My experience with our development team in Dubai: in between business, SOA and sun]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.org/my-experience-with-our-development-team-in-dubai-in-between-business-soa-and-sun/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-29T18:08:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.org/my-experience-with-our-development-team-in-dubai-in-between-business-soa-and-sun</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I had the opportunity to share with the
people at the <a href="http://www.phptostart.it/">PHP.TO.START</a>
in Turin my 1-year experience in Namshi, one of
Rocket Internet&rsquo;s ventures in the Middle East.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="left" src="/images/phptostart2013.jpg"></p>

<p>Luckily, this was a great opportunity to meet some good
old friends and the talk went very well: of course,
the reharsal at the <a href="http://roma.grusp.org">PHP User Group in Rome</a>
earlier this week was a bless.</p>

<p>It basically deals with the phases that I experienced
with our team in Namshi, with some spicy details on
recruiting (from looking for talents to conducting
interviews), how to <strong>change processes to help people improving</strong>
(and not change people to improve processes) and
a big picture on what we were able to plan and achieve
in this year together, from a technical point of view.</p>

<p>At the end of the talk I invited everyone interested, and
I will repeat myself here, to look for the open positions
on <a href="http://en-ae.namshi.com/careers/">our careers site</a>,
since we are currently hiring a Lead Developer and a
PHP Developer (a junior or an intermediate, it&rsquo;s more
about the approach rather than the hands-on experience).</p>

<p>Here are the slides of the talk, in a slightly better (and more colored)
version compared to the ones I used in Rome:</p>

<iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/odino/slideshelf" width="760px" height="570px" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:none;" allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A brief visit to the cold lands of Italy]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.org/a-brief-visit-to-the-cold-lands-of-italy/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-29T14:14:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.org/a-brief-visit-to-the-cold-lands-of-italy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m enjoying a relatively long &ndash; at least for me &ndash; 2 weeks &ldquo;vacation&rdquo;
back in Italy, since I was missing my friends in Rome
since <strong>exactly</strong> a year and the last time my parents saw me it
was 6 months ago.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Fun thing is, since I can&rsquo;t miss the opportunity
of getting back in touch with a few people, I will
be joining 4 tech events:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://rome.codemotionworld.com/">Codemotion</a> &ndash; already happened, I was there on the 23rd &ndash; the conference open to
all the programming languages, in Rome</li>
<li><a href="http://roma.grusp.org/">PHP User group Rome</a>, a meetup that is held monthly, for one of
the user groups that I helped launching here in Italy, again in Rome, where I gave
a talk about assembling a mid-sized PHP team</li>
<li><a href="http://www.phptostart.it/">PHP.TO.START</a> &ndash; happening <strong>right now </strong>&ndash; a yearly event for the
north-western italian PHP community, where I&rsquo;ll be presenting the same talk I had at
the PUG Rome</li>
<li><a href="http://friuli.grusp.org/">PHP User Group Friuli</a>, another meetup organized by one of the
italian PHP User Groups, where I&rsquo;ll be presenting an <em>unknown</em> topic (at least for now)</li>
</ul>


<p>An <strong>important thing</strong>: I am actively recruiting for our company,
<a href="http://en-ae.namshi.com/careers/technology/">Namshi</a>, so if you
are interested in one of the open positions that we have right now
(in particular, Lead Developer and PHP Developer), feel free to approach
me if you find me at the upcoming events (in Turin and Udine).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Video introduction about NoSQL graph databases and OrientDB]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.org/video-introduction-about-nosql-graph-databases-and-orientdb/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-08T15:56:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.org/video-introduction-about-nosql-graph-databases-and-orientdb</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During October of the last year, me and my ex-colleague David
took some time off to partecipate to the <a href="http://phpcon.pl/2011/pl/">polish PHP Conference</a>
with a talk about graph databases, OrientDB and how to integrate it
in PHP.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I recently found out that the videos recorded at the conference
finally made it to Vimeo: enjoy some tarzan english!</p>

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/53451968?badge=0" width="720" height="600" frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p> <p><a href="http://vimeo.com/53451968">Alessandro Nadalin, David Funaro: Graph databases and PHP: time for serious stuff</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/user10854134">PLUG</a> on <a href="http://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a>.</p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mixing the history of HTTP, SPDY and HTTP/2.0]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.org/mixing-the-history-of-http-spdy-and-http-slash-2-dot-0/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-16T15:11:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.org/mixing-the-history-of-http-spdy-and-http-slash-2-dot-0</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, from Doha&rsquo;s international airport, I
got the chance to blog about the latest changes
surrounding the upcoming major version of the
protocol of the web, <code>HTTP/2.0</code>.</p>

<p>Today I gave, at the International PHPConference in
Mainz, an overview about HTTP (<code>0.9</code>, <code>1.0</code>, <code>1.1</code>), SPDY
and <code>HTTP/2.0</code> itself.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>There&rsquo;s not that much to say, as the presentation is already
on <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/odino/http-colon-slash-slash-the-end-of-the-road">Slideshare</a> and I&rsquo;m embedding it here, other than a thing
the guys here in Germany already heard a lot: <strong>go back to
the basics</strong>.</p>

<p><div class="slideshare" id="__ss_14749994"><iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/14749994 " width="850" height="730" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ready for europe, IPC and pizzas]]></title>
    <link href="http://odino.org/ready-for-europe-ipc-and-pizzas/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-14T21:21:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://odino.org/ready-for-europe-ipc-and-pizzas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 24 hourse I&rsquo;ll be on a plane which is gonna bring
me in Frankfurt, to then join the <a href="http://phpconference.com/">International PHP Conference</a>
in Mainz.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="right" src="/images/ipc-slide.png"></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m pretty excited since this will be my first visit
to the old continent since I moved to Dubai &ndash; almost 7 months ago &ndash;
and I&rsquo;m glad I&rsquo;ll do that for IPC, with a brief <em>pit-stop</em> in Italy &ndash;
unfortunately not in Rome.</p>

<p>At IPC I will talk about REST, with an &ndash; I hope &ndash;
interesting introduction about this architectural style, anti-patterns
and a few tips on how to implement REST&rsquo;s constraints in our
architectures.</p>

<p>I will also have another chance to talk, and I&rsquo;m <strong>seriously</strong>
excited about it, since, for the first time, I get the chance to
talk about the foundation of our lives in the modern era (<em>homo internectus</em>),
the <strong>HTTP protocol</strong>: I will talk a little bit about why we needed it,
with some historical notion about the web&rsquo;s foundation, what SPDY
brings on the table and the recent <strong>revolutions</strong> around <code>HTTP/2.0</code>.</p>

<p>On the 17th evening I will catch a flight for Venice (via Wien) and then
I&rsquo;ll spend some time with the rest of the family, good thing if you also
consider that for the first time in 4 years they&rsquo;re gonna see me for my birthday.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/ale_idiot.jpeg"></p>

<p>But Italy doesn&rsquo;t mean that I&rsquo;m going to relax <strong>at all</strong>, as I will
finally meet all the guys from the <a href="http://friuli.grusp.org/">PHP User Group Friuli</a>,
the 2nd PHP user group in Italy (considering numbers and history), that
I personally founded along with <a href="http://www.mvassociati.it/it/il-team">Steve&amp;Stefano</a> and <a href="http://it.linkedin.com/in/dlondero">Daniel</a> in front of a pizza,
but never got to join during their
monthly meetings, as I was already based in Rome at that time.</p>

<p>There is no plan about that meeting, as the topic will be &ldquo;<em>Alessandro Nadalin in tour</em>&rdquo;:
if you are a developer, a technology enthusiast or simply a student come
and join us in Codroipo, as I will also talk about abroad work experiences as well
as scout and recruit for some companies (yes, not only <strong>my</strong> company).</p>

<p>Cheers!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
