<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: conference | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.odino.org/blog/categories/conference/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-14T21:49:56+04:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ready for europe, IPC and pizzas]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.odino.org/ready-for-europe-ipc-and-pizzas/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-14T21:21:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.odino.org/ready-for-europe-ipc-and-pizzas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 24 hourse I'll be on a plane which is gonna bring
me in Frankfurt, to then join the <a href="http://phpconference.com/">International PHP Conference</a>
in Mainz.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="right" src="/images/ipc-slide.png"></p>

<p>I'm pretty excited since this will be my first visit
to the old continent since I moved to Dubai - almost 7 months ago -
and I'm glad I'll do that for IPC, with a brief <em>pit-stop</em> in Italy -
unfortunately not in Rome.</p>

<p>At IPC I will talk about REST, with an - I hope -
interesting introduction about this architectural style, anti-patterns
and a few tips on how to implement REST's constraints in our
architectures.</p>

<p>I will also have another chance to talk, and I'm <strong>seriously</strong>
excited about it, since, for the first time, I get the chance to
talk about the foundation of our lives in the modern era (<em>homo internectus</em>),
the <strong>HTTP protocol</strong>: I will talk a little bit about why we needed it,
with some historical notion about the web's foundation, what SPDY
brings on the table and the recent <strong>revolutions</strong> around <code>HTTP/2.0</code>.</p>

<p>On the 17th evening I will catch a flight for Venice (via Wien) and then
I'll spend some time with the rest of the family, good thing if you also
consider that for the first time in 4 years they're gonna see me for my birthday.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/ale_idiot.jpeg"></p>

<p>But Italy doesn't mean that I'm going to relax <strong>at all</strong>, as I will
finally meet all the guys from the <a href="http://friuli.grusp.org/">PHP User Group Friuli</a>,
the 2nd PHP user group in Italy (considering numbers and history), that
I personally founded along with <a href="http://www.mvassociati.it/it/il-team">Steve&amp;Stefano</a> and <a href="http://it.linkedin.com/in/dlondero">Daniel</a> in front of a pizza,
but never got to join during their
monthly meetings, as I was already based in Rome at that time.</p>

<p>There is no plan about that meeting, as the topic will be "<em>Alessandro Nadalin in tour</em>":
if you are a developer, a technology enthusiast or simply a student come
and join us in Codroipo, as I will also talk about abroad work experiences as well
as scout and recruit for some companies (yes, not only <strong>my</strong> company).</p>

<p>Cheers!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking at IPC 2012]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.odino.org/speaking-at-ipc-2012/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-23T19:34:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.odino.org/speaking-at-ipc-2012</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Now it's official: in October I will be
in Mainz for <a href="http://phpconference.com/">IPC 2012</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>No doubts anymore: I will be present - for my first time -
at the most prestigious<sup id='fnref:1'><a href='#fn:1' rel='footnote'>1</a></sup> european PHP conference,
a travel more than 6 thousand kilometers long:</p>

<iframe width="750" height="600" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" src="https://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;source=s_q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=FWObgQEd3exLAylFxtlqSUNfPjFiUSmEUG7mvQ%3BFZ7U-gId1dd9ACl5E98zLpG9RzGgG9sQ1dQiBA&amp;q=from+Dubai+to+Mainz&amp;aq=&amp;sll=32.93158,33.8919&amp;sspn=21.939821,46.538086&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;t=m&amp;saddr=Dubai&amp;daddr=Mainz&amp;ll=37.0008,31.761065&amp;spn=26.13436,47.12413&amp;output=embed"></iframe>


<p>I will bring with me a new talk<sup id='fnref:2'><a href='#fn:2' rel='footnote'>2</a></sup>, which
mainly deals with protocols:</p>

<ul>
<li>history of <code>HTTP</code></li>
<li>hiddent features of <code>HTTP/1.1</code></li>
<li>what should we expect from <code>HTTP/2.0</code></li>
<li>how <code>SPDY</code> is revolutionizing web protocols</li>
</ul>


<p>If you'll be there, dont hesitate and drop me a line
at <em>alessandro.nadalin@gmail.com</em>, it will be a good
opportunity to have a chat about PHP and the
<a href="/moving-to-dubai/">Middle East</a>.</p>

<p><div class="footnotes">
<span>
Notes
</span>
	<ol>
		<li id='fn:1'>Not a lot of doubts about this, which doesnt automatically make it the best european PHP conference: my memories of the PHP Benelux Conference 2011 are still alive <a href='#fnref:1' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li><li id='fn:2'>"HTTP colon slash slash: end of an era?" <a href='#fnref:2' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li>
	</ol>
</div>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Going beyond HTTP at IPC in October]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.odino.org/going-beyond-http-at-ipc-in-october/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-02T13:31:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.odino.org/going-beyond-http-at-ipc-in-october</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just a quick one: seems that in October I'll need to travel
all my way back to Europe to speak at the
<a href="http://phpconference.com/">international PHP Conference</a> 2012
in its winter edition.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Subject? Oh, something that I <em>really</em> love:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>For years we've been used to the HTTP protocol, one of the reasons behind the web's success, a protocol able to scale up to bilion of requests and beyond.<br/>But there's more we can achieve, leveraging HTTP/1.1 hidden feature, taking a look at HTTP/2.0 and SPDY, the Google-proposed new protocol which is already making web faster.</p></p><p><p>Back to the basics: what enpowers and will enpower the web?</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Still to be confirmed - flights, leave days, date - but I should be able
to make it for the first time among the germans.</p>

<p>Hope to see you there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OSIDays 2011 wrapup]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.odino.org/osidays-2011-wrapup/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-22T15:26:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.odino.org/osidays-2011-wrapup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There we go: I am in Bengaluru for OSIDays, and the conference is about to finish today, after cool and less cool moments.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>One hour of TDD: from saying hello to PHPUnit to mocking objects</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/osidays.jpg"></p>

<p>With my first talk I've messed a few things up: as I was plugging the VGA adapter to my laptop, the native screen was loosing signal so I needed to do my session with <a href="http://blog.bastian-feder.de/blog.html">Bastian</a>'s laptop (dude, you saved my ass).</p>

<p>The session went pretty well:  I gotta confess that I was a bit scared of showing some real-world code examples, step by step, in a live session, so the audience probably felt my preoccupation... after all, the talk quickly took the right direction, and I was able to show the <strong>implementation of the Dijkstra's algorithm in PHP with test-driven development</strong>.</p>

<p>The presentation is on <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/odino/got-units-osidays">slideshare</a> and you can clone the <a href="https://github.com/odino/osidays">repository on github</a> (slides/code without code/slides are useless).</p>

<h2>RESTful architectures</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/osidays2.jpg"></p>

<p>Oh, that was easy.</p>

<p>Not trying to sound arrogant, but this is probably the 8th time I give this presentation, so I'm pretty used to deliver it.</p>

<p>This edition of <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/odino/rest-in-peace-osidays-2011-india-11212011">REST in peace</a> is already on slideshare, and it contains a few new things from the other, older, presentations: if you followed me during this months of <em>RESTvangelization</em> you'll notice that a few concepts are getting more and more important, like having durable services and taking advantage of the greatest REST architecture, the Web.</p>

<p>The <strong>presentation went well</strong> and a few people actually came after the talk for <strong>having some insights</strong> about implementing a reverse proxy in their architectures and so on...   ...a rails guy even told me we was revisiting his opinion of RoR-powered APIs now :)</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/osidays3.jpg"></p>

<p>I was pretty disappointed by the number of people attending the session (~50) but, from what I saw, it was really complex, for the majority of the attendees, to <strong>understand concepts like evolvability and durability</strong> in a country like India, which is the greatest place in the world to outsource <strong>quick'n'dirty software</strong> ( I hope they're fixing it with this conferences and getting a better <em>forma mentis</em> from the software development point of view ).</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/osidays4.jpg"></p>

<p>The organization
Wow, one of the coolest aspects of the conference: they have been able to satisfy every need we had, from transportation to eating, via relaxing in a wonderful hotel.</p>

<h2>Other talks</h2>

<p>I attended a few sessions from other eurospeakers like <a href="http://www.hugohamon.com/en">Hugo Hamon</a>, <a href="http://blog.bastian-feder.de/blog.html">Bastian Feder</a> and the <em>evergreen</em> <a href="http://schlitt.info/.html">Tobias</a>: although I basically knew any concept presented there, I felt how those presentations were needed by the audience here at OSIDays, 'cause they are living the moment that PHP was living 6 years ago.</p>

<p>The point is that when you need to write crappy code, that should be production-ready in 48 hours, you don't test anything, you don't decouple anything, you don't design anything: programmers are now forced to work in this way, and the most proficient ones get hired by great companies like IBM or whatever major.</p>

<p>Participating at these conference should make the average indian developer aware of the fact that he has a possibility: to leverage his skills and try to build complex system, not only outsourced stuff.</p>

<p>I think this is a pretty difficult topic, because only a few of them had a real-world experience on what we call <em>ordinary</em> projects: without seeing them, they think that the procedural and messy way they have is a good compromise to get the job done.</p>

<h2>And now?</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/osidays5.jpg"></p>

<p>I don't talk about my personal life in this blog, so I will not tell you how things went from this point of view: let's just says that now I have 3 free days for visiting a few cities here in the southern part of India...   ...let's hope they will be amazing as a few moments here in Bengaluru.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jazoon 2011 wrapup]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.odino.org/jazoon-2011-wrapup/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-28T15:09:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.odino.org/jazoon-2011-wrapup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So, as you might know, the last week I've been in Zurich in order to partecipate to the Jazoon Rookie Award.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/jazoon1.jpg"></p>

<h2>The city</h2>

<p>Zurich, gotta say, is a really nice city: it has a lot of green and its quite clean: as Lukas told me, it's not because Swiss people are that respectful, but because the public administration hires lots of scavengers :)</p>

<p>Switzerland is also soooooooooo expensive, and, by the way, my hotel was in what they call "the gold coast of Zurich", the richest part of the city, so as I ordered a plate of ananas at a vegetarian restaurant, I was traumatized when paying: 30 euros or something like that ( note for the me of the future: remember before the departure's flight that Switzerland is not in the UE, so they don't have euros ).</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/jazoon2.jpg"></p>

<h2>The conference</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/jazoon3.jpg"></p>

<p>The Jazoon was pretty awesome: I had the opportunity to meet a lot of funny people and we had great time playing at the table-soccer or just chatting about the current state of sw lifecycles and other nerdy stuff.</p>

<p>The organization was really good, because at the hotel everyone knew about our arrival and the conference was easy to reach, with a perfect wi-fi connection and some recreative areas.</p>

<p>And, since I am italian I need to say it, the food was really tasty :)</p>

<h2>The award</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/jazoon4.jpg"></p>

<p>Oh, man, a really really really great experience.</p>

<p>I competed against Benjamin from Karlsruhe and Ivo from Skopje, 2 really cool guys that had really good presentations.</p>

<p>I ranked 2nd with my "REST in peace: a handbook of software waste" and won a Lenovo IdeaPad which is, basically... awesome :)</p>

<h2>Many thanks to...</h2>

<p>The other 2 rookies, we had a few beers and funny moments together, it was well-spent time with those guys.</p>

<p>And, obviously, a particular thank you to Georgios ( I hope the name is ok, George! ), Ivo's mentor - as far as I understood - a really nice person to chat with: we had a few moments to talk and it was really nice to have the opportunity to listen the point of view of such a wise and experienced guy.</p>

<p>Last but not least, a really big "thank you!" to Felix, Jutta and Marco from the organization, it was a pleasure to be invited at such this kind of conference.</p>

<h2>My presentation</h2>

<p>As usual, I post here the presentation, but you can find it on slideshare:</p>

<p><div class="slideshare" id="__ss_8392980"><iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/8392980 " width="850" height="730" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
