<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: conference | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.odino.org/blog/categories/conference/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-06T00:02:54+04:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking at IPC 2012]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.odino.org/speaking-at-ipc-2012/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-23T19:34:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.odino.org/speaking-at-ipc-2012</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Now it's official: in October I will be
in Mainz for <a href="http://phpconference.com/">IPC 2012</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>No doubts anymore: I will be present - for my first time -
at the most prestigious<sup id='fnref:1'><a href='#fn:1' rel='footnote'>1</a></sup> european PHP conference,
a travel more than 6 thousand kilometers long:</p>

<iframe width="750" height="600" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" src="https://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;source=s_q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=FWObgQEd3exLAylFxtlqSUNfPjFiUSmEUG7mvQ%3BFZ7U-gId1dd9ACl5E98zLpG9RzGgG9sQ1dQiBA&amp;q=from+Dubai+to+Mainz&amp;aq=&amp;sll=32.93158,33.8919&amp;sspn=21.939821,46.538086&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;t=m&amp;saddr=Dubai&amp;daddr=Mainz&amp;ll=37.0008,31.761065&amp;spn=26.13436,47.12413&amp;output=embed"></iframe>


<p>I will bring with me a new talk<sup id='fnref:2'><a href='#fn:2' rel='footnote'>2</a></sup>, which
mainly deals with protocols:</p>

<ul>
<li>history of <code>HTTP</code></li>
<li>hiddent features of <code>HTTP/1.1</code></li>
<li>what should we expect from <code>HTTP/2.0</code></li>
<li>how <code>SPDY</code> is revolutionizing web protocols</li>
</ul>


<p>If you'll be there, dont hesitate and drop me a line
at <em>alessandro.nadalin@gmail.com</em>, it will be a good
opportunity to have a chat about PHP and the
<a href="/moving-to-dubai/">Middle East</a>.</p>

<p><div class="footnotes">
<span>
Notes
</span>
	<ol>
		<li id='fn:1'>Not a lot of doubts about this, which doesnt automatically make it the best european PHP conference: my memories of the PHP Benelux Conference 2011 are still alive <a href='#fnref:1' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li><li id='fn:2'>"HTTP colon slash slash: end of an era?" <a href='#fnref:2' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li>
	</ol>
</div>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Going beyond HTTP at IPC in October]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.odino.org/going-beyond-http-at-ipc-in-october/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-02T13:31:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.odino.org/going-beyond-http-at-ipc-in-october</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just a quick one: seems that in October I'll need to travel
all my way back to Europe to speak at the
<a href="http://phpconference.com/">international PHP Conference</a> 2012
in its winter edition.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Subject? Oh, something that I <em>really</em> love:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>For years we've been used to the HTTP protocol, one of the reasons behind the web's success, a protocol able to scale up to bilion of requests and beyond.<br/>But there's more we can achieve, leveraging HTTP/1.1 hidden feature, taking a look at HTTP/2.0 and SPDY, the Google-proposed new protocol which is already making web faster.</p></p><p><p>Back to the basics: what enpowers and will enpower the web?</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Still to be confirmed - flights, leave days, date - but I should be able
to make it for the first time among the germans.</p>

<p>Hope to see you there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OSIDays 2011 wrapup]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.odino.org/osidays-2011-wrapup/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-22T15:26:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.odino.org/osidays-2011-wrapup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There we go: I am in Bengaluru for OSIDays, and the conference is about to finish today, after cool and less cool moments.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>One hour of TDD: from saying hello to PHPUnit to mocking objects</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/osidays.jpg"></p>

<p>With my first talk I've messed a few things up: as I was plugging the VGA adapter to my laptop, the native screen was loosing signal so I needed to do my session with <a href="http://blog.bastian-feder.de/blog.html">Bastian</a>'s laptop (dude, you saved my ass).</p>

<p>The session went pretty well:  I gotta confess that I was a bit scared of showing some real-world code examples, step by step, in a live session, so the audience probably felt my preoccupation... after all, the talk quickly took the right direction, and I was able to show the <strong>implementation of the Dijkstra's algorithm in PHP with test-driven development</strong>.</p>

<p>The presentation is on <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/odino/got-units-osidays">slideshare</a> and you can clone the <a href="https://github.com/odino/osidays">repository on github</a> (slides/code without code/slides are useless).</p>

<h2>RESTful architectures</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/osidays2.jpg"></p>

<p>Oh, that was easy.</p>

<p>Not trying to sound arrogant, but this is probably the 8th time I give this presentation, so I'm pretty used to deliver it.</p>

<p>This edition of <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/odino/rest-in-peace-osidays-2011-india-11212011">REST in peace</a> is already on slideshare, and it contains a few new things from the other, older, presentations: if you followed me during this months of <em>RESTvangelization</em> you'll notice that a few concepts are getting more and more important, like having durable services and taking advantage of the greatest REST architecture, the Web.</p>

<p>The <strong>presentation went well</strong> and a few people actually came after the talk for <strong>having some insights</strong> about implementing a reverse proxy in their architectures and so on...   ...a rails guy even told me we was revisiting his opinion of RoR-powered APIs now :)</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/osidays3.jpg"></p>

<p>I was pretty disappointed by the number of people attending the session (~50) but, from what I saw, it was really complex, for the majority of the attendees, to <strong>understand concepts like evolvability and durability</strong> in a country like India, which is the greatest place in the world to outsource <strong>quick'n'dirty software</strong> ( I hope they're fixing it with this conferences and getting a better <em>forma mentis</em> from the software development point of view ).</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/osidays4.jpg"></p>

<p>The organization
Wow, one of the coolest aspects of the conference: they have been able to satisfy every need we had, from transportation to eating, via relaxing in a wonderful hotel.</p>

<h2>Other talks</h2>

<p>I attended a few sessions from other eurospeakers like <a href="http://www.hugohamon.com/en">Hugo Hamon</a>, <a href="http://blog.bastian-feder.de/blog.html">Bastian Feder</a> and the <em>evergreen</em> <a href="http://schlitt.info/.html">Tobias</a>: although I basically knew any concept presented there, I felt how those presentations were needed by the audience here at OSIDays, 'cause they are living the moment that PHP was living 6 years ago.</p>

<p>The point is that when you need to write crappy code, that should be production-ready in 48 hours, you don't test anything, you don't decouple anything, you don't design anything: programmers are now forced to work in this way, and the most proficient ones get hired by great companies like IBM or whatever major.</p>

<p>Participating at these conference should make the average indian developer aware of the fact that he has a possibility: to leverage his skills and try to build complex system, not only outsourced stuff.</p>

<p>I think this is a pretty difficult topic, because only a few of them had a real-world experience on what we call <em>ordinary</em> projects: without seeing them, they think that the procedural and messy way they have is a good compromise to get the job done.</p>

<h2>And now?</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/osidays5.jpg"></p>

<p>I don't talk about my personal life in this blog, so I will not tell you how things went from this point of view: let's just says that now I have 3 free days for visiting a few cities here in the southern part of India...   ...let's hope they will be amazing as a few moments here in Bengaluru.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jazoon 2011 wrapup]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.odino.org/jazoon-2011-wrapup/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-28T15:09:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.odino.org/jazoon-2011-wrapup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So, as you might know, the last week I've been in Zurich in order to partecipate to the Jazoon Rookie Award.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/jazoon1.jpg"></p>

<h2>The city</h2>

<p>Zurich, gotta say, is a really nice city: it has a lot of green and its quite clean: as Lukas told me, it's not because Swiss people are that respectful, but because the public administration hires lots of scavengers :)</p>

<p>Switzerland is also soooooooooo expensive, and, by the way, my hotel was in what they call "the gold coast of Zurich", the richest part of the city, so as I ordered a plate of ananas at a vegetarian restaurant, I was traumatized when paying: 30 euros or something like that ( note for the me of the future: remember before the departure's flight that Switzerland is not in the UE, so they don't have euros ).</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/jazoon2.jpg"></p>

<h2>The conference</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/jazoon3.jpg"></p>

<p>The Jazoon was pretty awesome: I had the opportunity to meet a lot of funny people and we had great time playing at the table-soccer or just chatting about the current state of sw lifecycles and other nerdy stuff.</p>

<p>The organization was really good, because at the hotel everyone knew about our arrival and the conference was easy to reach, with a perfect wi-fi connection and some recreative areas.</p>

<p>And, since I am italian I need to say it, the food was really tasty :)</p>

<h2>The award</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/jazoon4.jpg"></p>

<p>Oh, man, a really really really great experience.</p>

<p>I competed against Benjamin from Karlsruhe and Ivo from Skopje, 2 really cool guys that had really good presentations.</p>

<p>I ranked 2nd with my "REST in peace: a handbook of software waste" and won a Lenovo IdeaPad which is, basically... awesome :)</p>

<h2>Many thanks to...</h2>

<p>The other 2 rookies, we had a few beers and funny moments together, it was well-spent time with those guys.</p>

<p>And, obviously, a particular thank you to Georgios ( I hope the name is ok, George! ), Ivo's mentor - as far as I understood - a really nice person to chat with: we had a few moments to talk and it was really nice to have the opportunity to listen the point of view of such a wise and experienced guy.</p>

<p>Last but not least, a really big "thank you!" to Felix, Jutta and Marco from the organization, it was a pleasure to be invited at such this kind of conference.</p>

<h2>My presentation</h2>

<p>As usual, I post here the presentation, but you can find it on slideshare:</p>

<p><div class="slideshare" id="__ss_8392980"><iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/8392980 " width="850" height="730" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PHPDay 2011 wrapup]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.odino.org/phpday-2011-wrapup/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-09T15:33:00+04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.odino.org/phpday-2011-wrapup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's been a while since I got back from the PHPDay ( ~1 month ) and the experience definitely deserves a post.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Where, when, how..</h2>

<p>This year's PHPDay has been held in Verona, the wonderful place where Romeo and Juliet had their drama.</p>

<p>The location was the same of the 2009 edition ( which, BTW, was the first conference as a speaker, for me ) with the addition of the third day, just like the last year.</p>

<p>The conference had a first day of workshops and the last 2 days of tutorials and talks: 25 minutes for the former, 45 for the latter.</p>

<h2>Day 1: the german track</h2>

<p>Very curious, the workshop day had an entire track with german speakers: Sebastian Bergmann gave a nice <a href="http://www.phpday.it/2011/session/testing-lamp-applications">overview of PHPUnit 3.5</a> with the addition of a live example testing legacy code.</p>

<p>The guys from Quafoo presented the <a href="http://www.phpday.it/2011/session/any-any-convert-your-documents">document component from the Apache Zeta Components</a>: seems pretty awesome, given that document conversion is something everyone of us faces during his career and everyone of us blamed TCPDF at least once.</p>

<p>Quafoo again showed us their <a href="http://www.phpday.it/2011/session/generic-php-application-installer">application installer</a>, which is an high-level library able to let developers code their own installer according to common needs ( database setup, filesystem configuration and so on ).</p>

<h2>Day 2: tremendous keynote</h2>

<p>My second day started with a topic we're facing in our company: the hard combination between <a href="http://www.phpday.it/2011/session/just-married-user-centred-design-and-agile">agile development and user-centered design</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.phpday.it/2011/session/many-many-no-man-island">Jacopo Romei</a> had an embarassing ( with a positive meaning ) keynote about collaboration and communities: one of the coolest I ever heard, given that I often find keynotes boring.</p>

<p>In the first session of the afternoon I presented the <a href="http://www.phpday.it/2011/session/be-lazy-be-esi-http-caching-and-symfony2-0">HTTP cache inside Symfony2</a>, pretty satisfied about the people listening and their feedbacks.</p>

<p>Then I listened about 2 build systems, <a href="http://www.phpday.it/2011/session/phing-vs-ant-parola-chiave-automatizzare">Phing and Ant</a>: an insteresting italian talk, given that I didn't know that a few code metrics tools are well-integrated with this kind of systems.</p>

<h2>Day 3: leaving Verona with style</h2>

<p>My attention was firstly captured by the <a href="http://www.phpday.it/2011/session/symfony-e-grandi-numeri-si-pu-fare">real-world report about calciomercato.com</a> ( that can be translated in soccertrades.com ), a site, built with symfony 1.4, which scored 4 milions visits in August 2010: definitely impressive.</p>

<p>The talks wasn't obviously focused on the software architecture but on the system architecture behind the website: a cool thing was that they prefered to build 2 separate machine templates ( you usually have 1 VM template, that you scale horizontally ), one used to serve the website and the other for the static assets, some kind of a little CDN.</p>

<p>Giorgio Sironi had an interesting talk about <a href="http://www.phpday.it/2011/session/pursuing-domain-driven-design-practices-php">DDD in PHP</a>: it was a real pity that there were a few guys listening him, because DDD is - obviously - coupled with doing OO right, and PHPers often forget about them both.</p>

<p>During the afternoon I had the great occasion to present, with David, an overview about the <a href="http://www.phpday.it/2011/session/cmf-pain-f">problems relational DBMS have with fuzzy-model softwares</a>, like CMSes: it has been an opportunity to show off that <a href="http://www.dnsee.com/">DNSEE</a> guys are working hard to develop a CMF based on Symfony2 and a NoSQL graph database, OrientDB.</p>

<h2>So what?</h2>

<p>Once again, the best conference I ever attended, did not betrayed my expectations.</p>

<p>If you want to view the slides of the talks, have a look at the <a href="http://joind.in/event/view/472">Joind.in</a> page.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
