<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Category: Productivity | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="https://odino.org/categories/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2021-07-24T08:15:36+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[#OffFacebook: Half a Year Later]]></title>
    <link href="https://odino.org/number-offfacebook-half-a-year-later/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-20T16:46:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://odino.org/number-offfacebook-half-a-year-later</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/fb-art.png"></p>

<p>At the end of last year I decided to try completely removing Facebook from my life:
truth to be told, FB does a great job at letting you disconnect by deactivating
your account and decide when to come back &mdash; so it was an easy experiment.</p>

<p>In this post I&rsquo;d like to report a few observations 5 months down the line.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>What, and how</h2>

<p>Long story short, I de-activated my account and kept it as such for a good month.
In February I then re-activated it and observed how much time I would spend on
the platform on a daily basis.</p>

<p>I basically wanted to see what would have changed by removing such a sometimes useless,
sometimes crucial app from my life, and I was fairly pleased with my findings.
Nothing groundbreaking, but it gave me a good idea of what facebook is really
good for and how I should spend my time on the platform.</p>

<h2>Moving to another social media platform</h2>

<p>As soon as I de-activated my account, I noticed a &ldquo;void&rdquo;: I would leave work and
tap on the blue icon &mdash; only to see a login screen asking me to re-activate my
account. I resisted, and turned my attention towards a different social media
platform: <a href="https://twitter.com/_odino_">twitter</a>.</p>

<p>I generally like twitter more as it provides more &ldquo;useful&rdquo; content: articles,
random strangers' observations around general topics and more professional
content overall. Since disconnecting from facebook, I&rsquo;d say 50% of the time I used
to spend there is now dedicated to twitter, which makes me feel a bit better about
how I spend my (dead) time.</p>

<h2>Vulpem pilum mutare, non mores</h2>

<p>Since re-activating my account in February I started spending more and more time
back on FB: for the first couple of weeks I would open it every couple of days or
so, and for the first month I didn&rsquo;t even open it up from my laptop.</p>

<p>Nowadays, I&rsquo;m back at it on a daily basis: you might think that&rsquo;s a fairly bad outcome,
but my usage of FB has, quite drastically, changed. Earlier, I used to spend time
scrolling through my feed searching for the elusive interesting post from an acquaintance
I haven&rsquo;t seen in 10 years, whereas now I open the app, check my notifications,
close it &mdash; much less time wasted away.</p>

<h2>Reading, reading, reading, read&hellip;</h2>

<p>Related to the &ldquo;void&rdquo;, I again found myself with a lot of time beside twitter:
while commuting to work, right after waking up, while brushing my teeth&hellip;</p>

<p>I went back to <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/">HackerNews</a>: I used to devour HN on a daily basis, while over the past year
I spent more time on my <a href="/categories/book/">kindle</a> and focused
less on the daily inspiration HN brings you. This was definitely a plus for me,
as I have now found the time for both books and tech news.</p>

<h2>Disconnecting from everyone</h2>

<p>One of the negative points was that a few people only get in touch through FB,
and at that point I cut them out <em>just like that</em>. You now how I noticed it?</p>

<p>Enter my dad:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/dad-fb.png"></p>

<p>Should be easy to translate but, just in case:</p>

<blockquote><p>Hi. Did you close FB?</p></blockquote>

<p>Stunned, I went back and re-activated my account as I &mdash; ehm &mdash; felt quite bad. I&rsquo;m quite
terrible at keeping in touch with people, and seeing pops asking me whether I was on
FB or not made me realize he was probably gonna share some interesting NBA highlight
with me, only to notice I wasn&rsquo;t available&hellip;</p>

<h2>Unlike THAT!</h2>

<p>I also noticed a pattern once back on FB: I was truly annoyed at the amount of
random posts from pages I had liked in my teens that would pop in my feed.
I found myself valuing my time far more, and started to &ldquo;unlike&rdquo; those pages like
there&rsquo;s no tomorrow.</p>

<p>Not sure how to describe it but, since I re-activated my account I started to dislike
time-wasters much more than the usual. Guess it&rsquo;s not a bad thing after all.</p>

<h2>What next?</h2>

<p>As I mentioned, I don&rsquo;t think FB is (that) evil &mdash; it&rsquo;s just a matter of knowing
how and when to use it. My relationship with the social network is in a much better place (in my opinion,
which is probably not aligned with the advertisers') &mdash; sort
of <em>it&rsquo;s not you, it&rsquo;s me</em> kind of thing.</p>

<p>I would recommend you try to get off the hook for a few days, until you don&rsquo;t even
bother tapping on the blue icon out of habit. I learned how valuable FB can be when
keeping in touch with individuals who use it as a primary mean of communication,
and I&rsquo;m probably spending the least amount of time on FB since I joined the platform
(fun fact: when I joined I used to write in 3rd person &mdash; I guess it was a thing back then).</p>

<p>Advertisers crying in 3, 2&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>