<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ios | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="https://odino.org/categories/ios/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2022-11-18T09:33:53+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mobile Development's Future Is a Big Question Mark]]></title>
    <link href="https://odino.org/mobile-developments-future-is-a-big-question-mark/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-28T18:48:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://odino.org/mobile-developments-future-is-a-big-question-mark</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the past 5 years, mobile devices have taken
the world by storm, creating new opportunities
for both consumers and vendors: truth is, the
landscape of mobile <strong>development</strong> still looks
very immature and we should be prepared to see a
radical change in the next 2 to 5 years.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>A suboptimal development industry</h2>

<p>As we all agree, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duplicate_code">duplication is something bad</a>
in software engineering: it leads to unmaintainable,
error-prone code that requires a signicant effort
to be fixed.</p>

<p>If you are a mobile factory or a product-company
with its own apps-development team, you might be
familiar with the annoying problem of fixing, or
implementing, the same thing twice.</p>

<p>Nowadays, unfortunately, <strong>duplicate efforts are the norm
while developing mobile apps</strong>: you have to reproduce
the same behaviour across different platforms (ios
and android, but add blackberry or windows phone if you&rsquo;re
not that lucky) which led people to create tools like
<a href="http://cordova.apache.org">cordova</a>.</p>

<p>Problem is, these tools ain&rsquo;t the solution: they don&rsquo;t work
as nicely as native apps, they probably hide too
much from the developer and vendors aren&rsquo;t keen
on supporting them that much. If you, like me,
gave stuff like <a href="http://ionicframework.com/">ionic</a> a try,
you probably first found yourself surprised by
how nice your demo app would look and behave,
to then just find out that <strong>the more you were
implementing, the quirkier it looked</strong>.</p>

<p>On another note, the decision on how to structure
the team isn&rsquo;t trivial as well: shall
I get devs who can hack on both
platforms? Let&rsquo;s create 2 separate teams? Shall I
get 2 lead developers or 1 guy that has a good
sense on how both platforms work?</p>

<p>We need things to be better: just like the web,
mobile is now a scary land of vendors-dictated
&ldquo;standards&rdquo;. <strong>We don&rsquo;t need another JavaScript.</strong></p>

<h2>The need for standards</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t think mobile is much different to what
JavaScript used to look like until 3/5 years ago:
a lot of vendor-specific standards, weird tools
that try to uniform these platforms and a plethora
of things that just don&rsquo;t feel &ldquo;right&rdquo;.</p>

<p>We need uniform APIs, we need to be able to rely
on the same toolchain (for example, official <a href="https://support.google.com/googleplay/android-developer/answer/3131213?hl=en">staged rollouts</a> on the Apple Store)
and we need the same kind of transition the JS
ecosystem has seen: vendors need to
come together and design all of these things
altogether, agree on a minimal interface to share
and get ready to kill the mess.</p>

<p>Of course, there are a bit more complications here,
as we are talking about very different platforms,
with different development tools and workflow, which
is why I think we will see huge changes, from this
point of view, in the next 3 years.</p>

<h2>How will it look like?</h2>

<p>I have been telling people for a while that I do not
believe this multi-platform, fragmented ecosystem
can last for long, as I think it will eventually
lead vendors to agree on a common platform to work on.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t necessarily think it needs to be Objective-C,
but it definitely <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/androiddev/comments/27mu3v/why_do_android_dev_tools_still_suck/">won&rsquo;t be Android on Java</a>.
At the same time, I don&rsquo;t know how interested Apple
would be in making Swift / Objective-C a thing for the
masses (<a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/7133728/objective-c-in-linux">the masses are interested though</a>).</p>

<p>At the end of the day, thinking of <strong>one, unified mobile
platform</strong> seems kind of crazy today but, in 5 years,
devs would look back and wonder &ldquo;how could we do it like
that, to be wasting efforts on so many different platforms?&rdquo;.</p>

<h2>My personal feeling?</h2>

<p>At the end of the day, all we need is to give a popular
language a simple API to be able to completely access
your device.</p>

<p>That language&rsquo;s name is probably JavaScript<sup id='fnref:1'><a href='#fn:1' rel='footnote'>1</a></sup>.
And that API is probably something like <a href="http://trac.webkit.org/wiki/JavaScriptCore">JavaScriptCore</a>.</p>

<p>Since <a href="http://www.railslove.com/stories/fresh-on-our-radar-react-native">React Native</a>
seems to be already halfway through the journey of
making all of this real, my feeling is that it won&rsquo;t
take long until vendors will realize that the
easiest thing to do is to <strong>give JavaScript a (real) shot</strong>.</p>

<p>KTHXBYE.</p>

<p><div class="footnotes">
<span>
Notes
</span>
	<ol>
		<li id='fn:1'>I know that it sounds a bit counter-intuitive since I earlier said that &ldquo;we don&rsquo;t need another JavaScript&rdquo;, but there I was referring to what JS used to look like 3/5 years back (= a mess). We&rsquo;ve come a long way, though there&rsquo;s still a lot we can do :)  <a href='#fnref:1' rev='footnote'>↩</a></li>
	</ol>
</div>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>