<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rant | Alessandro Nadalin]]></title>
  <link href="https://odino.org/categories/rant/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://odino.org/"/>
  <updated>2022-02-21T09:37:30+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://odino.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alessandro Nadalin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Netflix, You Have a Problem]]></title>
    <link href="https://odino.org/netflix-you-have-a-problem/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-14T20:43:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://odino.org/netflix-you-have-a-problem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the story of how Netflix is really
trying to be funny&hellip;no, super-funny!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I&rsquo;ve ran a Netflix account for quite some
time but, after moving from Rome to Dubai
I stopped using the service as it would mean
using a VPN and stuff like that which is quite
against my principle of keeping things simple.</p>

<p>In the past months, while checking the statements
from my italian bank, I noticed that Netflix
kept billing me (cool), so I decided to try unsubscribing
from here, which turned out to be impossible.</p>

<p>Since I forgot my password, I tried recovering it:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/netflix-password-recovery.png"></p>

<p>Ok, no worries &mdash; it might be that I used another email!</p>

<p>A quick look into my inbox revealed that I was
going to face hard times:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/netflix-joining.png"></p>

<p>I used my regular email but still, Netflix
was refusing to let me in from their global
website. Could it be that their customer DB is
a bit messed up? Maybe if I go for the social
login I&rsquo;ll be able to get into my account:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/facebook-netflix.png"></p>

<p>Should have never tried this one, ya? It amazes me
how they cannot even provide complete error
messages.</p>

<p>So here I am, unable to unsubscribe from a service
I am not using anymore; the only reasonable thing
was to try reaching out to these guys and ask them
what to do: I did that <a href="https://twitter.com/_odino_/status/468734390537687040">once</a>,
then a <a href="https://twitter.com/_odino_/status/465149059691339776">second time</a> and,
just to be sure, I tried it <a href="https://twitter.com/_odino_/status/528982644688564225">a couple months ago</a> as well.</p>

<p>All attempts went unheard: it was clear by now that
<strong>Netflix didn&rsquo;t really seem to care that much</strong>.</p>

<p>Luckily, the credit card I used to sign up expired
this month and Netflix could not charge me anymore.</p>

<p>That meant receiving one of the most sarcastic emails
ever:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/netflix.png"></p>

<p>No, Netflix, <strong>you</strong> have a problem.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>